<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hollandi posthuma A funerall elegie of King Iames: With a congratulatory salve to King Charles. An elegie of the magnanimous Henry Earle of Oxford. A description of the late great, fearefull and prodigious plague: and divers other patheticall poemes, elegies, and other lines, on divers subiectes. The post-humes of Abraham Holland, sometimes of Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge. The authors epitaph, made by himselfe.</title>
            <author>Holland, Abraham, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849370</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849370</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1177:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hollandi posthuma A funerall elegie of King Iames: With a congratulatory salve to King Charles. An elegie of the magnanimous Henry Earle of Oxford. A description of the late great, fearefull and prodigious plague: and divers other patheticall poemes, elegies, and other lines, on divers subiectes. The post-humes of Abraham Holland, sometimes of Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge. The authors epitaph, made by himselfe.</title>
                  <author>Holland, Abraham, d. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Printed by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet] Impensis, Henrici Holland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cantabrigiæ [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A collection, mostly in verse, by Abraham Holland. Privately printed in a limited impression at Holland's expense--National Union Catalog.</note>
                  <note>The place of publication is false; actual place of publication and printer's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes the following (each with a 1626 separate dated title page): An elegie: or, some post-hume teares, vpon the the royall hearse of our late sovereigne Iames; An elegie vpon the death of the right noble and magnanimous Heroë, Henry Earle of Oxford, Vnto these post-humes is added: Naumachia. Or, a poeticall description of the cruell and bloudie sea-fight or battaile of Lepanto. Also includes a poem on the plague (with caption title: "The description of the late great memorable and prodigious plague. 1625") that was reprinted in STC 6175.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]²  (a)⁴ B-M⁴ ² A²  ² B-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; the British Library copy lacks M3 (M3 and other leaves supplied at end from the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library copy and Folger Shakespeare Library copy).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oxford, Henry de Vere, --  Earl of, 1593-1625 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lepanto, Battle of, 1517 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>HOLLANDI <hi>Post-huma.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A FVNERALL <hi>ELEGIE</hi> OF KING IAMES: WITH A CONGRATVLATORY <hi>Salve</hi> TO KING CHARLES.</p>
                  <p>An <hi>Elegie</hi> of the Magnanimous <hi>HENRY</hi> Earle of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Deſcription of the late great, fearefull and and Prodigious <hi>Plague:</hi> and divers other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall <hi>Poemes, Elegies,</hi> and other Lines, on divers ſubiects.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Poſt-humes</hi> of ABRAHAM HOLLAND, ſometimes of <hi>Trinity-Colledge</hi> in CAMBRIDGE.</p>
                  <p>The Authors <hi>EPITAPH,</hi> made by himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>CANTABRIGIAE, Impenſis, HENRICI HOLLAND. 1626.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:2"/>
                  <head>The Names or Titles of the enſuing ELEGIES, &amp;c.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>AN <hi>Elegie</hi> or ſome Poſt-hume teares for King <hi>IAMES: and</hi> A Congratulatorie <hi>Salve</hi> to King <hi>CHARLES.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>An Elegie on the Death of the Magnanimous <hi>HENRY</hi> Earle of <hi>Oxford,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>A Poeme written in the late Plague-time, to divers the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors endeered worthy Friends, then in the Countrey.</item>
                     <item>A Deſcription of the late great and prodigious Plague.</item>
                     <item>A Satyricall Poeme againſt one that did falſly accuſe the Author to the late Lord Keeper, of a Libell againſt <hi>IOHN OVVENS</hi> Monument in <hi>Pauls.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Poeme of his owne deere Father being Sicke.</item>
                     <item>A Poeme to his Friends in his owne ſickneſſe, with a reſolution againſt Death.</item>
                     <item>A Letter, ſavouring of Mortification, written in the time of the late Viſitation of the Plague, to his deere Brother <hi>H.H.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Confeſſion of his ſinnes to God, with a teſtimony of his Faith.</item>
                     <item>A metricall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſion of part of the <hi>73.</hi> Pſlame.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>T. C.</hi> the Authors endeered friend, his poeticall Verſion of the <hi>91.</hi> Pſalme.</item>
                     <item>A Meditation on the <hi>6.</hi> Pſalme, verſe <hi>4.</hi> and <hi>5.</hi> With ſome other Meditations in his Sickneſſe, and a Prayer.</item>
                     <item>His Bodies <hi>Vale</hi> to his best Part.</item>
                     <item>His Epitaph made by himſelfe.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND HIGH-BORNE HEROE, GEORGE, LORD GORDON, EARLE OF ENGIH: AND CAPTAINE OF THE GVARDDV-CORPS (commonly called IEAN DV-GVARD) to his Majeſtie of FRANCE: Sonne and Heire apparant, to the moſt Noble and Valerous the Marquiſse of <hi>HVNTLEY.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y LORD: The <hi>Author</hi> of theſe <hi>Poemes</hi> and other Lines, my deere Brother, being lately Deceaſed, and I loth that his Elaborate workes ſhould die, &amp; be buried in Oblivion, thought good rather to commit them to the
<pb facs="tcp:14511:3"/>
Preſſe, And doe make bold to make choiſe of your Noble Selfe, deſiring you to deigne the Patronage of them: And I am induced ſo to doe in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; Firſt, becauſe your Honour is the Prime <hi>Mecaenas</hi> of the <hi>Muſes,</hi> of your Noble Ranke, that I know, of <hi>Great Britaine</hi>: Secondly, for that I am not ignorant of you Honours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable and benigne acceptance of ſome other the Authors <hi>Poemes,</hi> from his owne hands. Why ſhall I then doubt of your Acceptance of theſe? The Orphanes of him, who to ſay no more, whiles hee had breath, as he was much obliged, ſo did highly prize and honour your Lordſhip.</p>
                  <p>Vouchſafe therefore, moſt Noble Lord, not onely the Patronage hereof againſt the malevolent detractors and vulgar mouthes (if any ſuch there be)
<pb facs="tcp:14511:3"/>
but the pardoning of my audacitie herein, beeing altogether unknowne unto you.</p>
                  <p>Now, Noble SIR, as the World knowes you were one of King IAMES his <hi>Northerne WORTHIES</hi>; ſo, who will denie but our gracious King CHARLES accompts you no leſſe? And that your Honour, Name and Fame, are not confined within the Empire of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> appeares by that thrice honorable Office conferred on you by the moſt <hi>Chriſtian French King:</hi> I pray GOD giue you increaſe of Honour on Earth, and hereafter immortall Honor in Heaven. And ſo, I humbly take my leaue of your Noble Lordſhip.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours moſt obſequious to be Commanded: <hi>H. H.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:4"/>
                  <head>TO The ingenious and ingenuous <hi>Reader,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as were the deceaſed Authors Friends.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLEMEN,</hi> I haue enterpriſed to commit theſe enſuing Lines, my deceaſed Brothers Orphanes, vnto the Preſſe, at mine owne proper Charges, not to make them common; for I hold them better worth than to bee expoſed to the vulgar View of euery <hi>Ignoramus</hi> or <hi>Non-intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git:</hi> The world already beeing full fraught and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with ſtuffe fit for their vnderſtanding. What theſe are, I need not tell you that knew the Author; And for your ſakes principally haue I made this Impreſsion, of no more Copies than I thinke to diſtribute vnto yee, his (and ſome of mine owne) endeered &amp; worthy Friends. I hope you will vouchſafe them benigne Acceptance, and me condigne thankes: by which, I ſhall bee encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to publiſh other his larger Labours which I haue lying by mee. And ſo I wiſh you all an heartie <hi>Vale,</hi> and of you take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours to Command. <hi>H. H.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>MICHAEL DRAYTON</hi> Eſquire, and Poet-Laureat, in Commendation of the <hi>AVTHOR</hi> and his firſt publiſhed Poeme, NA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MACHIA.</head>
                  <l>BY this one Lim, my HOLLAND, wee may ſee</l>
                  <l>What thou in time at thy full growth mayſt bee,</l>
                  <l>Which Wit by her owne <hi>Symetrie</hi> can take,</l>
                  <l>And thy proportion perfectly can make</l>
                  <l>At thy Aſcendant: that when thou ſhalt ſhow</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe; who reades thee perfectly ſhall know</l>
                  <l>Thoſe of the <hi>Muſes</hi> by this little light</l>
                  <l>Saw before other where to take thy height.</l>
                  <l>Proceed, let not <hi>Apollo's</hi> ſtocke decay,</l>
                  <l>POETS and KINGS are not borne euery day.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <head>
                     <hi>E C.</hi> Maſter of Arts, vpon the ſame.</head>
                  <l>SEnd forth, young-man, from <hi>Muſes</hi> wombe,</l>
                  <l>Thy other Royall <hi>Births</hi> at home,</l>
                  <l>But ſlowly, ſlowly ſend them forth,</l>
                  <l>Leſt for their number and their worth</l>
                  <l>The enuious hand of Fates take hold,</l>
                  <l>And crop thee; for they'le thinke th'art Old.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. W. I C.</hi> Vpon the ſame.</head>
                  <l>THat this ſmall <hi>Piece</hi> the World ſhould hazard firſt,</l>
                  <l>Of other better Workes thy <hi>Muſe</hi> hath nurſt</l>
                  <l>To wonder I was forc't, unleſs't bee done</l>
                  <l>As a ſmall Starre doth uſher forth the Sun.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <head>
                     <hi>E.P.</hi> Theologus, amico ſuo ARAHAMO HOLLANDO, D. PHILEMONIS F. in <hi>NAVMACHIAM</hi> ſuam.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>NAumachiam</hi> luſtrando tuam, <hi>mihi</hi> flumine viſus,</l>
                  <l>Iugenij placido deſperijſſe tui:</l>
                  <l>Arma virum, tabulas Guleas, &amp; Scuta per <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>das</l>
                  <l>Aſpicio, &amp; mens eſt Carmine merſa ſimul.</l>
                  <l>Emergo! &amp; tabulas votiuas dedico Muſae,</l>
                  <l>Docte <hi>HOLLANDE</hi> tua, quae bene facta canit.</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:5"/>
                  <p>AN <hi>ELEGIE:</hi> OR, SOME POST<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HVME TEARES, VPON THE ROYALL HEARSE OF OVR LATE SOVEREIGNE IAMES, KING OF <hi>GREAT BRITAINE, France,</hi> and <hi>Jreland</hi>; Defender of the <hi>Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Who Died at his Manour of THEOBALDS, the XXVII. of <hi>March,</hi> 1625.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>ABRAHAM HOLLAND.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed for HEN. HOLLAND. M.DC.XXVI.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:6"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>TO THE RIGHT HIGH &amp; MIGHTIE CHARLES, OF <hi>GREAT BRITAINE, France,</hi> and <hi>Jreland</hi>; the firſt King (of that Name) and ſecond Monarch: Defender of the FAITH, &amp;c.</salute>
                     <salute>Sole Inheritor of his Royall Fathers KINGDOMES and VERTVES. <hi>AND To King</hi> IAMES <hi>his Jmmortall Memorie.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>This <hi>Elegie</hi> is Conſecrated by his Sacred Majeſties humbleſt and meaneſt Subject.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="elegy">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:7"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:7"/>
                  <head>AN ELEGJE: OR, Some Poſthume teares, vpon the Royall Hearſe of our late Soueraigne King IAMES.</head>
                  <l>NOw that the Land hath nigh forgot to weepe,</l>
                  <l>And IAMES the <hi>Good</hi> more peaceably doth ſleepe</l>
                  <l>In his vnblamed Vrne, and th'Vniverſities,</l>
                  <l>Vpon his Hearſe from their lamenting eyes</l>
                  <l>Haue throwne their Pearles, &amp; through the widdow'd Towne</l>
                  <l>The curious wits haue jewelled his Crowne,</l>
                  <l>Pardon if now poore I doe ſpend a teare,</l>
                  <l>Though farre vnequall to my care, to beare</l>
                  <l>My ſorrow company, if I commence</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Nania</hi> now, and end it two yeares hence,</l>
                  <l>I'le chide my griefe, which could ſo ſoone expreſſe</l>
                  <l>It ſelfe by ſpeech, when ſpeech makes ſorrow leſſe.</l>
                  <l>Hee's dead; if ſome preciſer man ſhould aske</l>
                  <l>Who 'tis I meane, tell him that is a taske</l>
                  <l>A mortall cannot anſwer; let him flie</l>
                  <l>To be reſolu'd firſt to Phyloſophy,</l>
                  <l>And there make ſearch, what skilfull nature can</l>
                  <l>Invent that's curious to produce a man</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:8"/>Next, and moſt like a Deitie: and hence</l>
                  <l>Riſe to a Metaphyſick excellence,</l>
                  <l>And tranſcend Nature, let him there ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>The ſoul's cleare faculties, as they roſe</l>
                  <l>Perfect from the Creatour, and withall</l>
                  <l>Know ſuch an one is dead, who did recall</l>
                  <l>All decay'd vertues: Who had he liu'd that day</l>
                  <l>When wiſe PROMETHEUS man-kinde form'd of clay,</l>
                  <l>Hee might haue bin the Stampe pure and refin'd,</l>
                  <l>T'haue molded off all future humane Kinde:</l>
                  <l>But how theſe ſparkes which nature firſt did frame</l>
                  <l>Were ripened by Time, and made a flame</l>
                  <l>What graces did accrew vnto the minde</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Him</hi> that's dead, when it was diſciplinde</l>
                  <l>And form'd by Arts additions, would require</l>
                  <l>Praemeditations long and workes intire,</l>
                  <l>As HOMER happly being deſir'd to cleere</l>
                  <l>What th'<hi>Ithacan</hi> or fierce ACHILLES were,</l>
                  <l>Could not their well-knowne Excellence deſcrie</l>
                  <l>Vnder an <hi>Iliad</hi> and an <hi>Odyſsie</hi>:</l>
                  <l>Nor VIRGILL tell what his AENEAS was,</l>
                  <l>Vntill his anſwer did make vp the Maſſe</l>
                  <l>Of full twelue Bookes: had now ſome Poet more</l>
                  <l>And purer fancies than thoſe <hi>Swans</hi> before</l>
                  <l>Euer injoy'd, he could but meanely ſing,</l>
                  <l>And weakely tell what was our now-dead King.</l>
                  <l>Hee was a Man, a King, a God, aboue</l>
                  <l>The reach of enuie fear'd alone for loue,</l>
                  <l>And yet hee's dead, hee that few dayes agoe</l>
                  <l>Had ſayd ſo much, had bin Great <hi>Britaines</hi> foe,</l>
                  <l>Alas 'tis paſt an <hi>Omen</hi> now, and Fate</l>
                  <l>Hath giuen vs a bad licence to relate</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:8"/>The hated truth, nor treaſon is't to ſay</l>
                  <l>His Funerall was kept on ſuch a day;</l>
                  <l>Wee need no Calculations now, or Art</l>
                  <l>of Starres to gather, when his mortall part</l>
                  <l>Will pay the due to nature, he hath paid,</l>
                  <l>And She hath him a full acquittance made</l>
                  <l>Of all his debt: and now much like a ſtrong</l>
                  <l>And nimble-winged Eagle, which hath long</l>
                  <l>Bin pent in ſome cloſe Cage, his vn-hous'd ſprite</l>
                  <l>On able Plumes hath tan'e a joyfull flight</l>
                  <l>Vp to the Sunne, while we poore men below</l>
                  <l>Gaze at the ſight, and after him can throw</l>
                  <l>Onely our vowes: O whither Thou by this</l>
                  <l>White Soule, art crowned in a Throne of bliſſe</l>
                  <l>That ſtandeth on Eternitie, and thence</l>
                  <l>With a new Power, as an intelligence</l>
                  <l>Doeſt rule ſome Orbe: or whether thou and thine,</l>
                  <l>Thy wiſdome and thy Clemencie doe ſhine</l>
                  <l>As a new Conſtellation, in ſome Sphere,</l>
                  <l>Where nor the Powre of winds and ſtormes appeare,</l>
                  <l>Or any Guſt: that heareth not the claſh</l>
                  <l>Of Thunder, ſees no lightnings ſulph'ry flaſh.</l>
                  <l>But there as in a pleaſing dreame doeſt lie</l>
                  <l>Bathed in bliſſe and fix'd Tranquillitie,</l>
                  <l>Hauing attained vnto that which Thou</l>
                  <l>So ſought'ſt on Earth, but full poſſeſs'd of now</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eternall Peace,</hi> while neighbouring Starres admire</l>
                  <l>To ſee ſo bright a gueſt increaſe their quire.</l>
                  <l>Or whether thou with Angells doeſt conſent</l>
                  <l>To hold an euerlaſting Parliament,</l>
                  <l>In robes as white as thoſe wherein the Quire</l>
                  <l>Of ſurpluſs'd Saints ſing Carolls and admire</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:9"/>Their Makers glorie ermin'd all with lights,</l>
                  <l>And ſtarres that glitter in ſereneſt nights,</l>
                  <l>The purple, not ſuch as the Tyrian ſhell</l>
                  <l>Doth yeeld, or th'high-pric'd Indian Cuchenel,</l>
                  <l>But ſuch as decks the proud <hi>Aurora,</hi> when</l>
                  <l>Shee ſhowes her bluſhing face to bed rid men,</l>
                  <l>Or ſuch as is for Coverlets diſpread,</l>
                  <l>To wearie Phoebus on his Weſterne bed.</l>
                  <l>Where er'e thou art, refined Soule, if ſo</l>
                  <l>The ſhades of men free'd from their priſon, Know</l>
                  <l>And ſee what's done on Earth, ô vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>And view the ſorrow of thy widow'd Land;</l>
                  <l>Pardon our Avarice if wee would faine</l>
                  <l>Enjoy our CHARLES? yet haue our IAMES againe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi> with one conſent would gladly view</l>
                  <l>A Heptarchy againe of ſuch as You</l>
                  <l>Without diuiſion: Much I cannot blame</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Idle Wizards, who did blindely ayme</l>
                  <l>At Truth they knew not, when it is agreed,</l>
                  <l>That now Thou art an an Emperour indeed,</l>
                  <l>And farre aboue a King; Thy <hi>Laureat</hi> ſoule</l>
                  <l>Being rid in triumph to her Capitoll,</l>
                  <l>Nor art thou fall'n, but as in pureſt nights,</l>
                  <l>In a full quire of Starres wee ſee ſome lights</l>
                  <l>Diſſemble ruine, which when man kinde ſaw</l>
                  <l>At firſt, it thought that Fate had broke the law</l>
                  <l>Of Nature, and let looſe thoſe rolling eyes,</l>
                  <l>Which be the Garriſon and centuries</l>
                  <l>To the braſſe Wall of heaven and doe keepe</l>
                  <l>Thoſe golden Vaults in a ſtill-waking ſleepe.</l>
                  <l>Thy Sonne is liuing, who is ſo miſ-led</l>
                  <l>While hee doth liue to ſay that Thou art dead?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:9"/>Shall wee here blame great Fate or loue it, which</l>
                  <l>Hath vs at once made both extreamely rich</l>
                  <l>And moſt deplored poore? which hath the ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of hidden India giuen vs, and more</l>
                  <l>Than er'e the pale and greedy Spaniard knew</l>
                  <l>In wretched <hi>Mexico,</hi> or rich <hi>Peru,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Where ambuſh'd rockes of Gold and ſiluer found</l>
                  <l>Looke pale and bluſh to leaue the guilty ground)</l>
                  <l>But hath bereau'd vs of a Mint, a Coine</l>
                  <l>That went for currant, vnto which did Ioyne</l>
                  <l>Refined Excellence: or, ſhall we ſay</l>
                  <l>By this our loſſe, that <hi>Fate</hi> did but diſplay</l>
                  <l>Her indiſcretion, which doth poize the States</l>
                  <l>Of men alike, and mighty Potentates?</l>
                  <l>The will of Deſtinie, which hath ſnatch'd away</l>
                  <l>The Weſterne Sunne, and yet remaines a Day</l>
                  <l>As bright as if it ſtill did here abide,</l>
                  <l>Hath ſtopt the Current, yet the ſtreame doth ride</l>
                  <l>In Chriſtall beautie; hath impli'de a Change</l>
                  <l>Without an alteration, yea, more ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Produc'd a joyfull ſadneſſe: that the while</l>
                  <l>Wee are a weeping, we doe oft beguile</l>
                  <l>The victorie of ſorrow with a gleame</l>
                  <l>Of preſent Ioy, like as a ſodaine beame</l>
                  <l>Strikes from a Tempeſt; you can paſſe no way,</l>
                  <l>But by th'occurrent, one may juſtly ſay</l>
                  <l>There's a ſtrange Conflict, a ſtrange Monſter bred,</l>
                  <l>Of Ioy and Sorrow ſtreaming from one head</l>
                  <l>The King: See, here comes on a drouping man</l>
                  <l>With anguiſh printed in his brow, pale, wan,</l>
                  <l>And onely mouing; aske him what's the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall heare him after a ſad pauſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:10"/>So well as griefe will giue him leaue, to ſay</l>
                  <l>The beſt of Kings, the beſt of men, this day</l>
                  <l>Hath left vs wretched Mortalls to deplore</l>
                  <l>That bliſſe, that peace, that wiſdome, which before</l>
                  <l>We knew not how to value, till the want</l>
                  <l>Tells vs how negligent and Ignorant</l>
                  <l>Wee were of ſo great happineſſe: Thus hee</l>
                  <l>Will make his ſorry anſwer, or may bee</l>
                  <l>Bee altogether ſilent to deſcrie</l>
                  <l>Th'importance of the new calamitie.</l>
                  <l>For greateſt miſeries which ſhould declare</l>
                  <l>Exceſſe of ſorrow, dumbe and ſilent are.</l>
                  <l>But doe I not through all the people heare</l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Omens,</hi> and glad acclamations teare</l>
                  <l>Th'aſtoniſh'd aire, ſo lowd and ſhrill, that <hi>Spaine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Germanie</hi> doe ſtand amaz'd againe:</l>
                  <l>An art of memorie would little aide</l>
                  <l>To recall ſorrow, when that word is ſay'd</l>
                  <l>King CHARLES: As when in ſome vncertain weather</l>
                  <l>Two diverſe windes doe joyne their blaſts together</l>
                  <l>The wauering Forreſts, and the Neuter Corne</l>
                  <l>You then may ſee, now this, now that way borne,</l>
                  <l>Still moſt inclining to the conquering blaſt</l>
                  <l>That did preuaile, and breathe vpon them laſt.</l>
                  <l>I doe confeſſe, the gaine of ſuch a King</l>
                  <l>Wee now enjoy, may well ſome ſolace bring</l>
                  <l>For our dead IAMES: Yet as wee often ſee</l>
                  <l>In a religious Groue ſome aged Tree,</l>
                  <l>As a long-liued Oke, or bald-head Elme,</l>
                  <l>Which not ſo many Stormes could ouer-whelme,</l>
                  <l>So many Keene and ſurly Winters rage,</l>
                  <l>But there it ſtands reſpected for the age,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:10"/>Although the armes and ſeared bough's doe fade,</l>
                  <l>And that it with the trunke doth make a ſhade</l>
                  <l>Rather than leaues: yet vnderneath the Faunes</l>
                  <l>And Syluan Gods from farre-remooued Launes</l>
                  <l>Shelter themſelues; and when it fall's the ſweet</l>
                  <l>And gentle Nymphs, and horn-hoof'd Satyres meet</l>
                  <l>To waile their loued Shed, which oft did tame</l>
                  <l>The rage of Iuly, and the Dog-ſtarres flame.</l>
                  <l>Could we ſuppoſe another Sun would riſe,</l>
                  <l>And make his Zodiack from the Southerne skies</l>
                  <l>And ſet i'th' North, leauing the Eaſt as chill</l>
                  <l>As th'Orcades, yet we ſhould thinke on ſtill</l>
                  <l>Our ancient freind the former Sun, whoſe power</l>
                  <l>So many a Spring, ſo many a joyfull houre</l>
                  <l>Produc'd before: ô! it is hard to ſay,</l>
                  <l>When Cuſtomarie vertue's tan'e away</l>
                  <l>How great the griefe is, though perhaps the bliſſe</l>
                  <l>That doth enſue to th'other equall is.</l>
                  <l>There is an old wiues Prouerbe that the <hi>Spring</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May make an <hi>Ague Phyſicke for a King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And God this Medicine did to him apply,</l>
                  <l>To cure him of diſeas'd mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>And ſettle him Eternall: where, nor age</l>
                  <l>Doth follow Time, as in this Pilgrimage</l>
                  <l>Of our ſad life, nor ſickneſſe, paine, or feare,</l>
                  <l>Or Decrement of beautie doth appeare,</l>
                  <l>But health eternall, and felicities</l>
                  <l>Without impaire, and Life that neuer dies.</l>
                  <l>What man hereafter that partaketh ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>But much more, reaſon, will wiſh reſidence</l>
                  <l>In this darke vale of life, where euery houre</l>
                  <l>Is ſpent or loſt, or ſubject to the power</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:11"/>Of dominiering Sinne, eſpecially</l>
                  <l>When thus good Kings, our Gods Tutelar die<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alas, while wee in this life trauaile fare,</l>
                  <l>Wee are but wretches hovering in the aire</l>
                  <l>With waxen Plumes, where feare ſtill leads the trace,</l>
                  <l>And too much heaven brings vs to earth apace,</l>
                  <l>To bring vs vnto heauen: we Comers are</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſodaine luſtre and prodigious haire</l>
                  <l>Affrights the world with wonderment, if we</l>
                  <l>Placed too high, or too inferiour bee.</l>
                  <l>Ah! who would truſt on the deceiuing ſtate</l>
                  <l>O<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſlipperie Crownes, held at as deere a rate</l>
                  <l>As often purchas'd, and againe reſign'd,</l>
                  <l>All-wayes with cares and anguiſh of the minde.</l>
                  <l>This great, good, wiſe, and learned Monarch, whom</l>
                  <l>The world affirm'd the Light of Chriſtendome:</l>
                  <l>The Northerne Starre and Wonder of his time,</l>
                  <l>Who was the moment of this Weſterne clime,</l>
                  <l>And held it in juſt poize: who did deviſe,</l>
                  <l>But now the Embryo's of Policies</l>
                  <l>Which Fate is ſtill a teeming: this good King</l>
                  <l>Alas, is come vnto his Evening;</l>
                  <l>And after ſoules and bodyes laſt divorce,</l>
                  <l>Lies in the Graue a cold vnlived Corſe.</l>
                  <l>Good Soule ſleepe ſweet, and quiet, and doe <hi>Thou</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That doeſt reviue, our King, ſmoothe vp <hi>that brow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That giues thy people life, doe <hi>Thou</hi> appeaſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy</hi> griefe, and the contagion will ceaſe</l>
                  <l>Of too much care: But if <hi>Thou</hi> ſtill doeſt keepe</l>
                  <l>Sorrow I'le ſweare hee's dead that does not weepe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Almightie God aſsiſt Thee, and the Windes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be Champions for CHARLES, what er'e He mindes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:11"/>
                  <p>AN ELEGIE VPON THE DEATH OF THE RIGHT NOBLE and Magnanimous <hi>Heroë,</hi> HENRY Earle of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Bulbec,</hi> Lord <hi>Samford,</hi> and Lord great Chamberlaine of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WHO SICKENED IN SERVICE OF HIS KING and Countrie, in defence of the States. And died at the <hi>Hagh</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> Aprill 1625.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>ABRAHAM HOLLAND.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed 1626.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:12"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE AND NOBLE LADY, <hi>DIANA,</hi> Counteſſe of OXFORD, Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ager of the Deceaſed <hi>HENRY</hi> Earle of OXFORD, Viſcount BVLBEC, Lord SAMFORD, and Lord great Chamberlaine of ENGLAND.</salute>
                     <salute>AND, TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE AND APPROVED Souldier, ROBERT VERE, the ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Earle of OXFORD, Heire apparant to the ſame Noble Titles and Honours.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>To both their Honours, This Elegie is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated.</p>
                  <byline>By <hi>H. H.</hi>
                  </byline>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="elegy">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:13"/>
                  <head>An Elegie upon the Death of the right Noble and Magnanimous <hi>HENRIE</hi> Earle of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Bulbec, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>WHat Starre was wanting in the Skie? what place</l>
                  <l>To be ſupplied anew? what empty ſpace</l>
                  <l>That requir'd OXFORD? was ſome Light growne dim,</l>
                  <l>Some Starre Decrepit that ſuborned Him</l>
                  <l>To darke the Earth by his Departure? Sure</l>
                  <l>The Thracian God to make his Orbe more pure</l>
                  <l>Hath borrow'd him; where in his fiery Carre</l>
                  <l>He ſhines a better MARS, a brighter Starre?</l>
                  <l>Or like a new Orion doth he ſtand</l>
                  <l>In Chriſtall Maile, and a bright blade in's hand</l>
                  <l>An armed Conſtellation, while the Quire</l>
                  <l>Of Pyrrhick dancers, with reflecting fire</l>
                  <l>Glitter on him? or like a Comets rage</l>
                  <l>Strikes he amazement on the trembling age?</l>
                  <l>Alas! theſe glorious fancies but expreſſe</l>
                  <l>His worth and our love to him, not make leſſe</l>
                  <l>The rape of Fate, while we poore Mortalls farre</l>
                  <l>More want ſuch men than heaven could want a Star.</l>
                  <l>Let Griefe then ſpeake, and for this wofull time</l>
                  <l>Let me nor ſtudie Number, Verſe, or rime,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:14"/>But write in fragments, ſo't ſhall be my due</l>
                  <l>Though not a Poet good, a Mourner true.</l>
                  <l>Though I ſhould ſay no more but, OXFORD's dead,</l>
                  <l>That would be made an Elegie, to ſpread</l>
                  <l>It ſelfe as farre as ſorrow, the Contents</l>
                  <l>Enlarg'd to Volumes, by the teares, laments,</l>
                  <l>And griefe in-generall, when the world affords</l>
                  <l>So vaſt a comment unto ſo few words.</l>
                  <l>Yee Powers above that looke on men with eyes</l>
                  <l>Iuſt and impartiall, if in Fate there lies</l>
                  <l>Still more revenge, ô let us wretches know</l>
                  <l>Our lot before, that we may weepe below</l>
                  <l>A timely expiation, and prevent</l>
                  <l>The torrent of thy wrath which now is bent</l>
                  <l>To make a Deluge or'e us, who have found,</l>
                  <l>Though after all Great IAMES was laid in ground,</l>
                  <l>A Plague, and OXFORDS Death: 'tis hard to ſay</l>
                  <l>Which of the two doth more our loſſe diſplay</l>
                  <l>The ruines both being Generall: and can</l>
                  <l>Heaven be ſo angrie with poore feeble man</l>
                  <l>To perſecute him further? No, the rage</l>
                  <l>Of Peſtilence which ſpreadeth through the age</l>
                  <l>Can ſcarce ſurpaſſe his loſſe: caſt feare away</l>
                  <l>Fate cannot teeme more miſchiefe; and muſt ſtay</l>
                  <l>Now at the height of Vengeance: OXFORDS death</l>
                  <l>Hath ingag'd heaven to ſpare the reſt beneath.</l>
                  <l>Who, what he living was thoſe men can tell</l>
                  <l>Who paſt the North and Southerne Poles doe dwell</l>
                  <l>I need not write it: that were but to ſhow</l>
                  <l>What we now want, and what we once did owe</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a man, whoſe like enſuing dayes</l>
                  <l>Shall ſcarce produce: Antiquitie may praiſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:14"/>Their HECTORS, and ACHILLES, with a dim</l>
                  <l>And fain'd applauſe, while we doe but right him</l>
                  <l>In their Encomiums. Who like a New-borne Starre</l>
                  <l>Bred us amazement onely, and from farre</l>
                  <l>Made us admire what he in time would bee,</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſhut up his Early light, while wee</l>
                  <l>Wonder that Fate could be ſo prodigall</l>
                  <l>So ſoone to ſhow, ſo quickly to let fall</l>
                  <l>So great a glorie; which we well may ſay</l>
                  <l>Had but an houre, a Minute, a ſhort day</l>
                  <l>That did deſerve an age: yea, ſome will ſay</l>
                  <l>As the beſt things, he made the ſhorter ſtay</l>
                  <l>T'expreſſe an Excellence: Yet alas, herein</l>
                  <l>We doe but flatter ſorrow and our ſin</l>
                  <l>Which tooke him hence; for had he ſtay'd till then</l>
                  <l>When there ſhould be no memorie left of men</l>
                  <l>H'had bin a Choice of heaven, and ſurpaſs't</l>
                  <l>The Annalls and the Chronicles, which vaſt</l>
                  <l>Vncertaine times have made: doe not ſurmize</l>
                  <l>That I herein am ſet t'Hyperbolize,</l>
                  <l>A ſtrict Hiſtorian of the time that ſay's</l>
                  <l>Leſſe, ſhall be held Detractour of his Praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Yea, future judgements when they ſhall compare</l>
                  <l>Him with the reſt ſhall call thoſe writers ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Who made him not a Patterne, as the blinde</l>
                  <l>Old HOMER, did ACHILLES, of his Kinde.</l>
                  <l>Alas 'twas nothing in the ancient time</l>
                  <l>For Noble men to raiſe their names, and clime</l>
                  <l>By hauty acts unto the top of Fame,</l>
                  <l>When as obeyſance to their Prince did claime,</l>
                  <l>And their owne Intereſts, that they ſhould ſhow</l>
                  <l>Not more what they adventur'd, than did owe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:15"/>When each day almoſt new invaſions, when</l>
                  <l>Civill diſturbance did compell the men</l>
                  <l>To a forc'd valour: In thoſe times to have</l>
                  <l>A TALBOT, ESSEX, or a DRAKE did ſave</l>
                  <l>The Countrie but from damage: but that now</l>
                  <l>When the now-Sainted IAMES had made a VOW</l>
                  <l>To bleſſe himſelfe, and us by making Peace:</l>
                  <l>That not all Spirit, and all MARS ſhould ceaſe</l>
                  <l>But ſuch a flame from thoſe ſtill aſhes riſe,</l>
                  <l>Did ſaue the Land from guilt of Cowardize.</l>
                  <l>Since OXFORD was a Youth, BELLONA ne're</l>
                  <l>Breath'd her allarmes in this our Hemiſphere,</l>
                  <l>But he purſu'd them, with a Noble fire</l>
                  <l>To fame his Countrie, and his owne deſire</l>
                  <l>Grounded on that: Great <hi>Venice</hi> and the Fates</l>
                  <l>Though luckleſſe of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with the <hi>States</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now fatall to him, and th'attempted Seas</l>
                  <l>Shall be his true, though Poſthumes witneſſes.</l>
                  <l>He ſought no new-made Honours in the Tide</l>
                  <l>Of favour, but <hi>was borne the ſame he di'de.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor came he to the Elyſium with ſhame</l>
                  <l>That the old VERES did bluſh to heare his Name</l>
                  <l>Brighter than theirs: where his deſerts to grace</l>
                  <l>His Grand-fathers roſe up and gave him place,</l>
                  <l>And ſet him with the Heroës, where the Quire</l>
                  <l>Of ayrie Worthies riſe up, and admire</l>
                  <l>The ſtately Shade: thoſe Brittiſh Ghoſts which long</l>
                  <l>Agoe were number'd in th'Elyſian throng</l>
                  <l>Ioy to behold him; SYDNEY threw his Bayes</l>
                  <l>On OXFORDS head, and daign'd to ſing his praiſe;</l>
                  <l>While Fame with ſilver Trumpet did keepe time</l>
                  <l>With his high Voice, and anſwered his rime.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:15"/>The ſoft inticements of the Court, the ſmiles</l>
                  <l>Of Glorious Princes the bewitching wiles</l>
                  <l>Of ſofter Ladies, and the Golden State</l>
                  <l>That in ſuch places doth on Greatneſſe waite</l>
                  <l>And all the ſhadie happineſſe which ſeemes</l>
                  <l>To attend Kings and follow Diadems</l>
                  <l>Were Boy-games to his minde: to ſee a Maske</l>
                  <l>And ſit it out, he held a greater taske</l>
                  <l>Than to endure a Siege: to wake all Night</l>
                  <l>In his cold armour, ſtill expecting fight</l>
                  <l>And the drad On-ſet, the ſad face of feare,</l>
                  <l>And the pale ſilence of an Army, were</l>
                  <l>His beſt Delights; among the common rout</l>
                  <l>Of his rough Souldiers to ſit hardneſſe out</l>
                  <l>Were his moſt pleaſing Delicates: to him</l>
                  <l>A Batter'd Helmet was a Diadem:</l>
                  <l>And wounds, his Brauerie: Knowing that Fame</l>
                  <l>And faire Eternitie could neuer claime</l>
                  <l>Their Meeds without ſuch Hazards: but alas</l>
                  <l>That wee muſt ſay, ſuch a Man OXFORD was,</l>
                  <l>A Hatefull Syllable which doth implie</l>
                  <l>Valour can be extinct and Vertue die.</l>
                  <l>O wer't not Profanation, I now</l>
                  <l>Could turne a ſtiffe Pythagoriſt and allow</l>
                  <l>A reall Metempſychoſis, if ſo</l>
                  <l>The Soule of OXFORD might divided flow</l>
                  <l>On much Nobilitie: and yet my ſect</l>
                  <l>Should honour finde from hence, they no Defect.</l>
                  <l>This was the yeare of Iubile in <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No meruaile, 'twas of griefe with us at home,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi> hath bin <hi>Romes</hi> Sacrifice, the whiles</l>
                  <l>Our Teares and Funerals haue bred their Smiles</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:16"/>A company of ſacred Soules before</l>
                  <l>Him left Mortalitie, as if the skore</l>
                  <l>Of Fate were quickly to be payd: but when</l>
                  <l>He left us wretches to continue men,</l>
                  <l>While hee himſelfe did to a Crowne attaine</l>
                  <l>The whole Quire ſeem'd in him to die againe:</l>
                  <l>As if h' had bin th' Epitome, and Briefe</l>
                  <l>Of all their Vertues, and of all our griefe:</l>
                  <l>But Fate did act this laſt and greateſt theft</l>
                  <l>To ſee if wee had any Sorrow left,</l>
                  <l>As if thoſe loued Soules which went before</l>
                  <l>Had ſpent our teares, and left our Eyes no more,</l>
                  <l>Alas, now pities us and bids us ſleepe</l>
                  <l>Seeing when Eyes are done our hearts can weepe.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaphs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:16"/>
                  <head>Two Epitaphs vpon the ſame Noble Earle.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="epitaph">
                     <head>EPITAPH. 1.</head>
                     <l>PAſſenger that needs wilt know</l>
                     <l>Who lyeth here</l>
                     <l>First let mee craue,</l>
                     <l>That thou, thy Pietie to ſhow</l>
                     <l>Let fall a teare</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Graue:</l>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>Oxford:</hi> whom when thou ſhalt finde</l>
                     <l>Entoomb'd below</l>
                     <l>Who late did liue,</l>
                     <l>Thou thy ſelfe ſhalt call vnkinde,</l>
                     <l>To haue bin ſo</l>
                     <l>Jnquiſitiue.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:17"/>
                     <head>EPITAPH. 2.</head>
                     <l>TO ſay that <hi>OXFORD</hi> here or there</l>
                     <l>Doth lye, confines a place</l>
                     <l>To his vnbounded Fame,</l>
                     <l>That Body which, you balme and ſeare</l>
                     <l>That Image you doe grace,</l>
                     <l>Js but his Shade, his Name.</l>
                     <l>What place of Heauen hath his Soule</l>
                     <l>And his diviner parts,</l>
                     <l>To mortals is vnknowne;</l>
                     <l>This wee may ſay without controll,</l>
                     <l>Jn all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts</l>
                     <l>His Toombe is made, though they bee made of Stone.</l>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="envoy">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:17"/>
                  <head>A L'envoy to my endeared Friends Mr. <hi>R.T.</hi> Mr.<hi>W.H.</hi> Mr.<hi>T.C.</hi> and others being in the Countrey. Seruing for an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to the Deſcription of the Plague.</head>
                  <l>DOe you not wonder that in this ſad time</l>
                  <l>I ſtill haue leyſure to compoſe a rime?</l>
                  <l>When as a Chriſtian care forbids me now</l>
                  <l>The helpe of Poetrie, that my hot brow</l>
                  <l>Should ſweate with actiue Wine, or that my heart</l>
                  <l>Should be ſo free from paſſion to vſe Art</l>
                  <l>Vnto my wilde expreſſions: The mirth</l>
                  <l>That entertaines a Muſe, and giues a Birth</l>
                  <l>To happy lines, is farre more fit for you</l>
                  <l>Who in your Countries happineſſe doe view</l>
                  <l>Our ſlaughters from a farre, as men in ſight</l>
                  <l>That ſtand remote ſpectators of a Fight.</l>
                  <l>Yet I would haue both you and all ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>Sorrow can ſpeake as well in verſe as proſe</l>
                  <l>In this <hi>great Yeare</hi> of <hi>Elegies:</hi> indeed</l>
                  <l>Not with that life, that flame, and actiue ſpeed.</l>
                  <l>As when Securitie did bid me play</l>
                  <l>With the ſmooth treſſes of <hi>Aſteria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And wander in her eyes: alas that theame</l>
                  <l>Is quell'd in griefe and drowned in the Streame</l>
                  <l>Of the times ſorrow: thoſe Heroïck layes</l>
                  <l>That were begun haue throwne away their bayes</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:18"/>And cloth'd themſelues in Cypreſſe; and my brow</l>
                  <l>Expects a Night-cap, more than Lawrell now.</l>
                  <l>Sirs you perhaps are chaſing o're the Fields</l>
                  <l>The Hare, the Deere, or what the ſeaſon yeelds</l>
                  <l>Doe Imp your Falcons wings, making it flie</l>
                  <l>A ſuttle ambuſher about the Skie.</l>
                  <l>We are the Prey of Death and each night ſtay</l>
                  <l>The call of Fate, untill the Morning ſay</l>
                  <l>We may draw forth a Noone; and ſo at Night</l>
                  <l>Lie downe againe not ſure of other light</l>
                  <l>Till the great Reſurrection: for may bee</l>
                  <l>Death hath his Writ this Night to ſerue on mee.</l>
                  <l>Doe you inquire whether wee be affraid</l>
                  <l>Of Death or no which ſo ſoone doth inuade</l>
                  <l>So ſurely Kill, I anſwer, no: that man</l>
                  <l>That liueth now and view's the ſtorme, and can</l>
                  <l>Still be affraid of Death, I muſt ſurmize</l>
                  <l>A Renegade, or full of Cowardize:</l>
                  <l>No Penitent can feare, and hee that ſtill</l>
                  <l>Retaines a heart unbroken acts more ill</l>
                  <l>Than all his life before: that ſoule is Steele</l>
                  <l>Which doth not bleed, that hell, which doth not feele</l>
                  <l>The preſent blow: It is with us who here</l>
                  <l>Hourely view death, as when exempt of feare</l>
                  <l>At an <hi>Oſtend</hi> or ſuch a Siege to die</l>
                  <l>The Souldiers thought it a Neceſſitie</l>
                  <l>And ſo did ſlight it, when each houre were ſhowne</l>
                  <l>So many others Death's t'aſſure their owne.</l>
                  <l>Endeared Friends, I am well and better much</l>
                  <l>And in more ſweet ſecuritie than ſuch</l>
                  <l>Who thinke of a long life, by theſe death's here</l>
                  <l>Being freed from what is worſe than death, the Feare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:18"/>Seldome is Chriſtian Valour better gain'd.</l>
                  <l>Than when 'tis by ſuch miſerie obtain'd.</l>
                  <l>I doubt not but that Fame which ſtill doth uſe</l>
                  <l>To ſpred abroad more large than certaine newes</l>
                  <l>Hath blaz'd our State, and haply doth aſſure</l>
                  <l>As you ſuppoſe farre more then we endure,</l>
                  <l>Thus farre let me your doubts herein ſuffice</l>
                  <l>Rumour it ſelfe can ſcarce Hyperbolize</l>
                  <l>Our Reall woe: Feare it ſelfe cannot vow</l>
                  <l>There is more Miſchiefe than wee ſuffer now:</l>
                  <l>If you ſhall heare of Streets wherein the Graſſe</l>
                  <l>Doth grow for want of men that uſe to paſſe</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Smithfield</hi> turn'd a medow or a plaine</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Horſes, Kine, and Sheepe againe</l>
                  <l>May feed rather than ſell: or of poore men</l>
                  <l>That in their Graues together lie by ten</l>
                  <l>By twenties or by more: or ſodaine Fates</l>
                  <l>Of people dying in the ſtreets and gates,</l>
                  <l>Doe not ſuppoſe it falſe, we wretches trie</l>
                  <l>What other Ages ſhall hold Poetrie,</l>
                  <l>A March in midſt of Auguſt, and the Star</l>
                  <l>That raigneth now farre from Canicular</l>
                  <l>In all but the effects; not cloth'd in bright</l>
                  <l>And ſcorching Sun-ſhine but in midſt of Night</l>
                  <l>And Winter ſtormes, as if the Plague did flie</l>
                  <l>Wrap't in thoſe clouds to fright the troubled Skie</l>
                  <l>And blaſt mortalitie: the ayre the while</l>
                  <l>Scarce in a Moneth ſtrikes forth one pleaſing ſmile</l>
                  <l>Muffled in damps, ſo cloſe that from beneath</l>
                  <l>Wee deeme it hard by any way but Death</l>
                  <l>To ſee bright Heauen againe: The Rurall ſwaines</l>
                  <l>Begin to doubt the Vſurie of their paines</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:19"/>And Propheſie a <hi>Famine</hi>: and the Earth</l>
                  <l>Choked with Carkaſſes threatens a <hi>Dearth</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As a Reuenge: The Skies the while doe ſhowre</l>
                  <l>Downe poyſonous tempeſt to augment the power</l>
                  <l>Of her pretended Malice: while the breath</l>
                  <l>Of blacke contagious windes doe tranſport Death</l>
                  <l>Through the enuenom'd ayre: Earth, Aire, and Skie</l>
                  <l>Conſpiring to our great Calamitie.</l>
                  <l>In what a caſe poore <hi>London</hi> ſtands, to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Would aske a Pen and Muſe that onely know</l>
                  <l>How to write griefe: alas it is become</l>
                  <l>A Theatre of Tragedies, where ſome</l>
                  <l>Di'de i'th' firſt acts, and many ſlaughters paſt</l>
                  <l>God knowes what murder ſhall be in the laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>I liue not in it, but in <hi>Chelſey</hi> aire</l>
                  <l>Where Death but in his Out-rodes doth repaire,</l>
                  <l>And thence doe onely heare the murmuring Bels</l>
                  <l>Diſcloſe the ſlaughter by the frequent Knels.</l>
                  <l>Yet as a tender Mother though ſhee haue</l>
                  <l>A Child interr'd, and ſleeping in the graue</l>
                  <l>Yet will ſhe oft goe ſee the tombe, and dew</l>
                  <l>His duſt with pious teares, and oft renew</l>
                  <l>His Poſthume exequies: ſo ſometime I</l>
                  <l>Goe to behold the Citie, and eſpie</l>
                  <l>As I doe walke along the widdow'd ſtreets</l>
                  <l>Nothing but ſorrow in each face that meets</l>
                  <l>In the Large ruine nothing but a griefe</l>
                  <l>That ſpeakes it ſelfe in ſilence, true and briefe.</l>
                  <l>Ah deere Sirs, it is changed from the Place</l>
                  <l>Yee knew it once, when as the beautious face</l>
                  <l>Of Gallantrie inrich'd the Streets, and Eyes</l>
                  <l>Of frequent beautie made it a Paradiſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:19"/>And the Delight of Nations, whoſe concourſe</l>
                  <l>Thither, and the Refluxe as from the Source</l>
                  <l>Of humane Kinde did make it ſeeme to bee</l>
                  <l>The Center of the World, the Worlds Epitome.</l>
                  <l>Death now alas hath not begun, but led</l>
                  <l>His Triumph through the Towne, and largely ſpred</l>
                  <l>His gloomy wings in circuit o're the Walls</l>
                  <l>Attended by ten thouſand Funerals</l>
                  <l>As if thoſe Pageants raiſed to renowne</l>
                  <l>Our deere Queenes Well-come, and great <hi>Charles</hi> his Crowne</l>
                  <l>Had bin of purpoſe made a Wofull throne</l>
                  <l>For Death and Fate to ſit ſpectatours on</l>
                  <l>When I ſee theſe, thinke you I can forbeare</l>
                  <l>But praiſe that God, who let's me ſtill be here</l>
                  <l>And makes me not a Spectacle, as they</l>
                  <l>That now are mine, and liu'd but yeſterday?</l>
                  <l>Deare Friends, it is not <hi>London,</hi> but the ſhade</l>
                  <l>And Carkaſſe of that place in aſhes layd.</l>
                  <l>Where you ſhall ſee in ſtead of ſport and play</l>
                  <l>A falſe yet as it ſeemes a Holiday,</l>
                  <l>The Doores ſhut up, and all the Streets about</l>
                  <l>But here and there a Paſſenger walke out</l>
                  <l>So ſolemne ſilence, that a man would ſay,</l>
                  <l>'Twere a light Night, or Seruice-time all Day:</l>
                  <l>The Bells as frequent as when oft they ſound</l>
                  <l>When a yong Prince is borne, or new King crown'd,</l>
                  <l>Which heard, a Stranger might be brought to ſweare</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Fift</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> or <hi>Nouember</hi> there</l>
                  <l>Were Solemnized now: which to aſſure</l>
                  <l>The Bon-fires almoſt euery night procure</l>
                  <l>A Shade of Ioy; which if you right will Know</l>
                  <l>As funerall Piles not ſolemne Bonfires glow</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:20"/>The Bells in their ſad language almoſt tell</l>
                  <l>They ring no Holiday, but ſpeake a Knell;</l>
                  <l>The Doores ſo ſhut that one in them might doubt</l>
                  <l>Whether it were to keepe Death in or out.</l>
                  <l>What Muſe ſhall I inuoke t'indite a rime</l>
                  <l>That may expreſſe our miſerable time?</l>
                  <l>Where the pale Viſages of men expreſſe</l>
                  <l>Farre aboue Poetrie the Heauineſſe</l>
                  <l>Of Gods ſharp Scourge, where the Red wand affrights</l>
                  <l>The Starring Paſſenger and troubled Nights</l>
                  <l>Are ſpent in Burials, when what e're we ſee</l>
                  <l>Is but an Argument of Miſerie;</l>
                  <l>The Wormwood-Noſegayes, &amp; the trembling Pace</l>
                  <l>Of them that paſſe, though they haue Herbe of Grace</l>
                  <l>And curious Boxes to repell the ayre</l>
                  <l>Which might aſſault them, ſeeming to out-dare</l>
                  <l>The will of Deſtinie: Nor can I blame</l>
                  <l>Our weake Mortalitie, which thinkes no ſhame</l>
                  <l>To ſhow a frailtie, deeming perhaps that Fate</l>
                  <l>Can yeeld to Soueraigne <hi>Bezoar,</hi> Mithridate</l>
                  <l>Or ſuch Death-killers, let us thinke ſo ſtill</l>
                  <l>So wee root out that weed of Sin and ill</l>
                  <l>Which taints our ſoules, ſo though for many yeares</l>
                  <l>It haue preuail'd, wee'l drowne it in our teares</l>
                  <l>And Kill this Giant Plague, which through the towne</l>
                  <l>As an unlooſed Lyon, beareth downe</l>
                  <l>What e're it meets, making no doubt to ſtrike</l>
                  <l>The cloudie Cedar and low Shrub alike:</l>
                  <l>So quicke and faſt that it makes men to ſay</l>
                  <l>'Twill not be long untill the Iudgement Day</l>
                  <l>Abſolue the Maſſacre, Death ſo doth ſhrine</l>
                  <l>To bring the Vniuerſe to light againe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:20"/>So few are borne to life ſo many Die</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lucina</hi> doth not Tith Mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>As if Death would not leaue untill for all</l>
                  <l>Doomeſday doe make one fire one funerall.</l>
                  <l>When now the Weeke-bills almoſt reach unto</l>
                  <l>The ſumme which that of th'yeare had wont to doe.</l>
                  <l>If from the Towne a Stranger ſhould but ſpie</l>
                  <l>How the affrighted People haſt to flie</l>
                  <l>In trembling heapes hee could not but ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>The ranſack'd Citie taken by the Foes,</l>
                  <l>And now poſſeſs'd, and the remaining rout</l>
                  <l>On a ſtrict compoſition flying out.</l>
                  <l>Enter the Citie you ſhall meet with there</l>
                  <l>A fearefull Valour, an audacious Feare,</l>
                  <l>Where men doe think't ſo difficult to ſcape</l>
                  <l>That they expoſe themſelues unto the rape</l>
                  <l>While they yet tremble, as if thence to flie</l>
                  <l>Were to giue wings to Death, and haſt to die.</l>
                  <l>A Noone in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> now can hardly ſhow</l>
                  <l>That Preſſe which Midnight could not long agoe;</l>
                  <l>No Proclamation needs the Gentrie haſt</l>
                  <l>Vnto their Homes, they doe it now too faſt</l>
                  <l>While the poore Sterued rout are taken hence</l>
                  <l>Alike by Famine and by Peſtilence.</l>
                  <l>Walke through the wofull Streets (whoeuer dare</l>
                  <l>Still venter on the ſad infected ayre)</l>
                  <l>So many Marked houſes you ſhall meet</l>
                  <l>As if the <hi>Citie</hi> were <hi>one Red-Croſſe ſtreet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Plague hath ſpred it ſelfe ſo vaſt and far</l>
                  <l>They need not ſet Markes in Particular</l>
                  <l>One very Doore, but to expreſſe the Loſſe</l>
                  <l>Not guild but red the Publike Citie croſſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:21"/>And briefe for all to ſhow the wrath of Fate</l>
                  <l>Set LORD HAVE MERCY ON's, on euery Gate.</l>
                  <l>Alas the little houſe hath loſt the Name</l>
                  <l>While wretched <hi>London</hi> may the Title claime</l>
                  <l>Of the great <hi>Peſt-houſe</hi>: where are buried more</l>
                  <l>Than wee had thought it had contain'd before:</l>
                  <l>That in our Iudgements it may well appeare</l>
                  <l>Turn'd from a Citie to a Sepulcher.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:21"/>
                  <head>The Deſcription of the late great memorable and prodigious Plague. <hi>1625.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GOod God! what poiſon lurkd in that firſt fruict</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſurfet left us wretches proſtitute</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a world of ſorrow? Not confin'd</l>
                     <l>Onely to teare and cruciate the minde</l>
                     <l>With ſad remembrance of the bliſſe, wherein</l>
                     <l>We might haue liu'd, but ſee the cruell Sin</l>
                     <l>Spares not our ſoules weake houſes, but doth ſpred</l>
                     <l>From viler parts unto the nobler head</l>
                     <l>A thouſand Maladies, which now alas</l>
                     <l>Through each ſmall In-let of the Bodie, paſſe</l>
                     <l>Remorſleſſe Enemies, and batter downe,</l>
                     <l>The clayie bulwarkes of our Mud-wall'd towne.</l>
                     <l>Our throat is like that vaſt breach, which doth bring</l>
                     <l>In like the <hi>Troian</hi> Horſe dire ſurfetting;</l>
                     <l>When in the Stomach like the Market-place</l>
                     <l>The foes let looſe dare ſpred themſelues, and trace</l>
                     <l>Through all the Citie, ſome are ready firſt</l>
                     <l>To breake the Sluces, which doe raging burſt</l>
                     <l>And drowne low buildings, ſome with flaming brands</l>
                     <l>Fire holy Temples, ſome with Swords in hands</l>
                     <l>Sharpe-pointed-Iavelins, Malls, and poiſonous darts</l>
                     <l>Make Maſſacres through all the trembling parts</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:22"/>Of the diſtreſſed Fabricke; no controll</l>
                     <l>Can barre'em but they will aſſault the Soule</l>
                     <l>It ſelfe almoſt, while each ſmall-breathing Pore</l>
                     <l>Betrayes unto the foe a Poſterne Dore</l>
                     <l>To enter in at, euery crawling veyne</l>
                     <l>Affords him harbour, and doth Entertaine</l>
                     <l>The bloudie Enemie, each Muſcle, Nerue,</l>
                     <l>And Filme makes him a Fortreſſe to preſerue</l>
                     <l>His longer Durance, till the gueſt at laſt</l>
                     <l>With ruine payes his Hoſt for all that's paſt.</l>
                     <l>How many ſuch foes, thinke you? Secret lye</l>
                     <l>When hundreds of them ambuſh in one Eye?</l>
                     <l>Which is the Lanthorne, and the Watch, and Light</l>
                     <l>Keepes Centurie for all the Bodies Night.</l>
                     <l>As ſoone may I exactly number all</l>
                     <l>The fainting leaues that in an Autumne fall,</l>
                     <l>The Creatures of the Summer, or the Store</l>
                     <l>Of wilder infects, which old <hi>Nilus</hi> ſhore</l>
                     <l>Each yeare produceth, as with Iudgement ſhow</l>
                     <l>How many fierce and bold diſeaſes flow</l>
                     <l>Vpon this wretched Carkaſſe, when each yeare</l>
                     <l>New troupes of raging Feuers domineere</l>
                     <l>That know no name, Each boy can nigh expreſſe</l>
                     <l>Diſeaſes now to Poſe <hi>Hippocrates.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Happy that age of gold, not onely 'cauſe</l>
                     <l>It had no vice, and ſo no need of Lawes,</l>
                     <l>When Nature was their <hi>Solon,</hi> and the want</l>
                     <l>Of Knowledge to doe ill, did make them Ignorant</l>
                     <l>Of the Redreſſe, not bleſs'd alone in this</l>
                     <l>Although the ayre and earth increas'd their bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>But that an able Bodie was combin'd</l>
                     <l>In a ſweet friendſhip with a harmeleſſe mind.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:22"/>They knew no Phyſicke (though their drugs did grow</l>
                     <l>Then in full vertue, able to beſtow</l>
                     <l>Health on this age) becauſe they Knew not how</l>
                     <l>To get thoſe Sickneſſes, which men Know now.</l>
                     <l>The Ague with a hundred names; the Aches</l>
                     <l>More than the Ioynts; the Palſey that attaches</l>
                     <l>The limbes with Diſſolution; the wild</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Bedlem</hi> Phrenſie: the Vertigo, ſtil'd</l>
                     <l>Becauſe it whirles the giddie braines about:</l>
                     <l>The ſweving Megrim; and the racking Gout:</l>
                     <l>The cruell Stone; the torturing Collicke fierce</l>
                     <l>And wringing winds, which through the lims diſperſe</l>
                     <l>Their ayrie torments; lingring diſpence</l>
                     <l>Of pale Conſumptions, which beſot the ſenſe:</l>
                     <l>The Deluge of a Dropſie: When ſhall I</l>
                     <l>Run through 'em all? the ſleepie Lethargie;</l>
                     <l>Quick-murdring Apoplexie which doth Kill</l>
                     <l>E're it makes Sicke: the piteous Falling-Ill:</l>
                     <l>The Elephant-skin'd Leproſie: Iaundies ſtaine:</l>
                     <l>Ambuſh'd Impoſtumes which ſurprize the braine:</l>
                     <l>With hart-aſſaulting Pleuriſies: the tough</l>
                     <l>And clutterd Flegme: and Rheume that breeds the Cough:</l>
                     <l>Strappado, Cramps; the ſodaine-pricking Stitch;</l>
                     <l>The Night-mare: which the people thinke a Witch,</l>
                     <l>Th'all conquering Pox, to which compar'd the reſt</l>
                     <l>Are Lady Sick-fits: this is that forraine gueſt</l>
                     <l>The Diuell-inſtructed <hi>Indies</hi> to us ſold</l>
                     <l>To recompence the filching of their Gold.</l>
                     <l>All theſe and more innumerable powers</l>
                     <l>Lay ſiege unto this weake-wall'd Fort of ours</l>
                     <l>And oft ſurprize an Out-worke, yea ſometime</l>
                     <l>In deſperate malice ready are to clime</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:23"/>The walls themſelues: till that the heart much like</l>
                     <l>A ſtrong Defendant maketh good the Dike</l>
                     <l>And giues 'em a repulſe: yet oft alas,</l>
                     <l>This noble Champion ſtaines the conquer'd Maſſe</l>
                     <l>With dying blood: For Sickneſſe is a Fight,</l>
                     <l>The victory doubtfull, Chances infinite.</l>
                     <l>But hath that power who is all Mercy, ſtill</l>
                     <l>More, and more cruell Puniſhments to Kill</l>
                     <l>Minute-liu'd man? yea, though you adde to theſe</l>
                     <l>Pale meager Famine, Murders of the Seas,</l>
                     <l>And Warres vaſt Slaughters; you ſhall find one more</l>
                     <l>That may affright the reſt wee nam'd before</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Plague,</hi> whoſe very naming ſeemes t'affright</l>
                     <l>My trembling Quill, as it doth haſt to write,</l>
                     <l>Leſt as it raging flies about the land</l>
                     <l>This Inſtant it might ſeaze vpon my hand:</l>
                     <l>The Plague a dreary Puniſhment, Heauens curſe,</l>
                     <l>The fatall Engine of Deſtruction, worſe</l>
                     <l>Than we can well imagine, which doth bring</l>
                     <l>Terrour on mortals, Death on euery thing,</l>
                     <l>And Deſolation unto Cities: O</l>
                     <l>What ere thou art, dire Ill, whether thou doeſt flow</l>
                     <l>From powerfull Influence of the Starres, or rather</l>
                     <l>Doeſt thy vaſt malice and contagion gather</l>
                     <l>From poiſonous Southerne windes, which haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail'd</l>
                     <l>Vpon the ſickly ayre, or Steames Exhal'd</l>
                     <l>From th'Earths enuenom'd wombe: or whether 't bee</l>
                     <l>Our Bodies Conſtitutions, which agree</l>
                     <l>With the malicious ayre and ſo contract</l>
                     <l>The quicke Infection: whether 't be the Pact</l>
                     <l>Of Fate, and will of Heauen which doth ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Or Gods immediate angry mooued hand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:23"/>As 'tis; O pull it in, thou Gracious Power,</l>
                     <l>And let not this blind Enemie deuoure</l>
                     <l>The Grace of <hi>England.</hi> CHARLES implores, wee</l>
                     <l>With him in zealous Oriſons agree:</l>
                     <l>Heare him for us, and us for him; and ſtay</l>
                     <l>Thy dreadfull vengeance, which doth now diſplay</l>
                     <l>Horror through all thy People, and begins</l>
                     <l>To ſhew the vgly portraict of our ſins,</l>
                     <l>Which haue pull'd downe thy wrath. O let ſuffice</l>
                     <l>That world of bloud in foreine Ayre that lyes,</l>
                     <l>Of noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſoules, whoſe carkaſſes</l>
                     <l>The brutiſh Shores, wild Fields, and greedie Seas</l>
                     <l>Expoſe to Dogs, to ravenous Fowles, and Fiſhes;</l>
                     <l>Ah, little anſwering to the tender wiſhes</l>
                     <l>Of their poore mothers, who at home the while</l>
                     <l>Gape at their childrens Honours, and beguile</l>
                     <l>Their early feares with too late hopes: alas</l>
                     <l>They little thinke, that now the ſoyled Graſſe</l>
                     <l>Vſurpes their deare embraces, and grim Fate</l>
                     <l>Sits pale vpon thoſe Beauties, which of late</l>
                     <l>They made their Ages comforts, who now ſhall</l>
                     <l>Ah! be bound to them for a Buriall.</l>
                     <l>O call to mind this Fatall Yeere, wherein</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Equally &amp; juſtly ſent.</note> Thy Iuſtice hath been equall to our Sin;</l>
                     <l>Both great: O let thy bleſſed Goodneſſe ſtill,</l>
                     <l>As it is wont to doe, ſurpaſſe our Ill.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe men whom we did love, whom we did truſt</l>
                     <l>Should be our Shields, are turn'd to Shades, to Duſt;</l>
                     <l>Let the in-throned Soule of IAMES implore,</l>
                     <l>That after Him, thou puniſh His no more:</l>
                     <l>Let the great Sprite of OXFORD, which hath paſt</l>
                     <l>The Sentence of thy Anger, be the laſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:24"/>Thou plagueſt vs withall; and let us know,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill thou pittieſt us, poore men, below.</l>
                     <l>But never let this Land endure againe</l>
                     <l>That wofull ſolitude, which once did raigne</l>
                     <l>In our faire Cities; which, neglected left,</l>
                     <l>In a deplored ruine, ſhew'd the theft</l>
                     <l>Of angrie Fate: when ſcarce a tenant Mouſe</l>
                     <l>Was left, in many a faire unpeopled houſe;</l>
                     <l>But the ſad Owles and Night-Ravens aloofe,</l>
                     <l>Did keepe their Revels on the ſilent roofe:</l>
                     <l>When at high Noone one paſſing by, ſhould meet</l>
                     <l>A Mid-night Darke, and ſilence in the ſtreet;</l>
                     <l>When in the wayes well-pav'd and worne before</l>
                     <l>By frequent ſteps of men, there now grew ſtore</l>
                     <l>Of uncouth Graſſe; and Harveſts now apace</l>
                     <l>Grew where they once were ſold, i'th'Market-place:</l>
                     <l>When as no Merryments, no Sports, no Playes</l>
                     <l>Were knowne at all, and yet all Holy-dayes.</l>
                     <l>No Papers then over the doores were ſet,</l>
                     <l>With, <hi>Chambers readie furniſh'd to be let</hi>;</l>
                     <l>But a ſad, <hi>Lord haue mercie vpon vs,</hi> and</l>
                     <l>A bloodie <hi>Croſſe,</hi> as fatall Marks did ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Able to fright one from the Prayer. The time</l>
                     <l>Then held it an inexpiable Crime,</l>
                     <l>To viſit a ſicke friend: Strange Stoure, wherein</l>
                     <l>Love was a fault and Charitie a ſin;</l>
                     <l>When Bad did feare infection from the Good,</l>
                     <l>And men did hate their cruell Neighbour-hood.</l>
                     <l>'Twas a deplored time, wherein the Skyes</l>
                     <l>Themſelves did labour, and let fall their eyes;</l>
                     <l>When one might ſee the Sunne, with ſallow hayre</l>
                     <l>And languiſhing complexion, dull the ayre:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:24"/>Looking eeu'n ſo, as when at <hi>Chryſes</hi> Plaint,</l>
                     <l>He went like Night, the <hi>Graecian</hi> troupes to taint</l>
                     <l>With ſad Infection; when his dire ſhafts caſt,</l>
                     <l>Kill'd more than <hi>Hector</hi> in the nine yeeres paſt.</l>
                     <l>The Heavens were cloth'd with bleak miſts, &amp; the aire</l>
                     <l>With the thick Dampe, was ſtruck into deſpaire</l>
                     <l>Of future cleareneſſe, or ſerener day,</l>
                     <l>But that the Clouds for feare ran oft away.</l>
                     <l>The Night, whoſe dewie ſhade had wont to tame</l>
                     <l>The ſoultry reliques of the Mid-day flame,</l>
                     <l>Diſtill'd no Cryſtall Pearles vpon the ground;</l>
                     <l>But wrapt in vaporous ſmoake, and cloath'd around</l>
                     <l>With poyſonous Exhalations, did affright</l>
                     <l>The trembling Moone; whoſe dim and paler light</l>
                     <l>Look'd with that countenance, as if againe</l>
                     <l>Her ſilver hornes ſhould ne're eſcape the Wane,</l>
                     <l>So to renew her Circuit. The dull Quire</l>
                     <l>Of ſickly Starres ſhew'd now no ſmiling fire,</l>
                     <l>But ſhone like un-ſnuff'd Tapers: as if Fate</l>
                     <l>Did give them leave now to prognoſticate</l>
                     <l>Their owne eſtate, not others; and applie</l>
                     <l>Themſelves at laſt to ſad Aſtrologie.</l>
                     <l>The poyſon-clutter'd Springs, with <hi>Plague</hi> infus'd,</l>
                     <l>Ran not with Cryſtall torrents, as they us'd;</l>
                     <l>But in dull ſtreames, as them dire influence fills,</l>
                     <l>With fainting pace, ſcarce reach'd unto their rills:</l>
                     <l>And languid Rivers, which before did paſſe</l>
                     <l>The Cryſtall with their cleareneſſe; now, alas,</l>
                     <l>Looke muddie, without ſtirring: and their ſtreames,</l>
                     <l>That wont to be all ſpangled with the beames</l>
                     <l>Of the blithe Sunne; now, in a weltring floud,</l>
                     <l>Ran not with water, but prodigious bloud.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:25"/>Thoſe Trees whereof the Antients us'd to rayſe</l>
                     <l>Their Funerall Piles, might in theſe fatall dayes</l>
                     <l>Burne at their owne Death's, which in ſad deſpayre</l>
                     <l>Spred not their leavie beauties through the ayre,</l>
                     <l>But ſuffer'd Autumne in the Spring: forlorne</l>
                     <l>And ferall Cypreſſe now had cauſe to mourne,</l>
                     <l>Poppeyes themſelves this time in death did ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>And the Myrrhe-tree had reaſon here to weepe</l>
                     <l>A Funerall Perfume: thoſe gaudie flowers</l>
                     <l>Which wont to make Ghirlonds for Paramours,</l>
                     <l>Mourn'd in their drouping braverie, and ſpread</l>
                     <l>The ground at their owne deaths, as for the dead.</l>
                     <l>The Corne grew not, as if it meant t'undoo</l>
                     <l>Men not with <hi>Plague</hi> alone, but <hi>Famine</hi> too.</l>
                     <l>Herbes, Phyſicks Soveraignes, here infected die,</l>
                     <l>And for themſelves could find no remedie.</l>
                     <l>The brute Beaſts now, which Nature, to beſtow</l>
                     <l>The Excellence on Man, did make with low</l>
                     <l>Downe-looking Poſtures, firſt did feele the rage</l>
                     <l>Of th'Earth-borne <hi>Plague,</hi> and died before their age.</l>
                     <l>The long-liv'd Hart this time to die began,</l>
                     <l>Before it reach'd unto the age of Man.</l>
                     <l>The faithfull Spaniell, by his death, did trie</l>
                     <l>The miſchiefe of his well-nos'd Facultie,</l>
                     <l>And ranging with quick Sent, did ſooneſt prove</l>
                     <l>Th'infectious Malice of the Dogge above.</l>
                     <l>The luſtie Steed, ſcouring in's Game apace,</l>
                     <l>Lights on Deaths Gole, in middle of his Race:</l>
                     <l>The nimble Fowle, as th'ayre it flyes around,</l>
                     <l>Flags his ſick wings, and ſinkes unto the ground,</l>
                     <l>Not long before to the remorſeleſſe Skie</l>
                     <l>In ſillie Notes have ſung his Elegie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:25"/>The luckleſſe Night-Ravens, which us'd to grone</l>
                     <l>The death of others, now might Dirge their owne:</l>
                     <l>The Snow-plum'd Swan, as it did gently ride</l>
                     <l>Vpon the ſilver Streame, ſung forth, and di'de.</l>
                     <l>Anon the Damp dares breake into the Walls,</l>
                     <l>Making a way by thouſand Funeralls:</l>
                     <l>Who can expreſſe th'aſtoniſhment and feare,</l>
                     <l>Which doth at entrance of a <hi>Plague</hi> appeare?</l>
                     <l>Even ſo the fleeced Heard doth tremble, when</l>
                     <l>An Aburne Lion, hungrie from his Den,</l>
                     <l>Breakes in among 'em: then you may behold</l>
                     <l>The pale-look'd Shepheard gaze upon his Fold</l>
                     <l>With helpeleſſe pitie, the poore Lam-kins creepe</l>
                     <l>Vnder their Dams; the ſillie trembling Sheepe</l>
                     <l>Stand full of cold amazement at the ſight,</l>
                     <l>Small hope for mercie, and leſſe hope in flight,</l>
                     <l>Expecting onely which of all ſhall ſcape</l>
                     <l>The readie horror of the Lions rape,</l>
                     <l>Other Diſeaſes warning give before,</l>
                     <l>That we may reckon, and acquit the Skore</l>
                     <l>Of our ſinnes Prodigalitie: in this,</l>
                     <l>We ſcarce can be reſolved whether 'tis</l>
                     <l>Sickneſſe, or Death it ſelfe; ſo quick it tries</l>
                     <l>The ſtrength of Nature, ſo ſoone poore Man dies:</l>
                     <l>That many to repoſe in th'Evening lying,</l>
                     <l>Have made their ſleepe true kin to Death, by dying</l>
                     <l>Before the Morne. Ah! who would then deferre</l>
                     <l>A preparation for this Meſſenger</l>
                     <l>Of bleſs'd or curs'd Eternitie? What man</l>
                     <l>Would ſtill preſume to ſinne, that knowes the ſpan</l>
                     <l>Of ſhort uncertaine Life? Yee gracious Powers,</l>
                     <l>That meaſure out the minutes and the houres</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:26"/>Of this our wandering Pilgrimage, reſtraine</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſodaine ſlaughter-men; or, good God waine</l>
                     <l>Vs from our ſinnes, that wee may neither feare</l>
                     <l>The rape of Death, nor covet to be here:</l>
                     <l>O curbe this raging Sickneſſe, which with ſenſe</l>
                     <l>Bereaves us of the meanes of Penitence.</l>
                     <l>When a dire Phrenſie ſeizeth on the Braine,</l>
                     <l>Full of reſiſtleſſe flame, and full of paine;</l>
                     <l>That Madneſſe, which no cure can well appeaſe,</l>
                     <l>Is but a Symptome, unto this Diſeaſe.</l>
                     <l>Our bloud all fire, as if it did portend</l>
                     <l>We were not here to ſtay, but ſoone aſcend;</l>
                     <l>When ſtreames of ſulphur through our veins do glide,</l>
                     <l>And ſcarce the ſenſe of ſorrow doth abide.</l>
                     <l>This time how miſerable, may we gueſſe,</l>
                     <l>Where want of ſenſe, is chiefeſt happineſſe:</l>
                     <l>When the diſtracted Soule can ſcarce deviſe</l>
                     <l>How to ſupply the weakeſt Faculties</l>
                     <l>Of the diſturbed Bodie; but preſents</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Eye ſtrange objects, ſtrange portents,</l>
                     <l>And antique ſhadowes: when the feveriſh rage</l>
                     <l>Sets us on Iourneyes oft, and Pilgrimage,</l>
                     <l>And entertaines our wild and wandering ſight</l>
                     <l>With monſtrous Land-ſchips, able to affright</l>
                     <l>A man in's wits: when the deceived Eares</l>
                     <l>Doe apprehend what ere the Fancie feares;</l>
                     <l>The grones of Ghoſts, and whiſpering of Sprites,</l>
                     <l>The ſilken tread of Faeries in the Nights,</l>
                     <l>The language of an ayrie Picture, howles</l>
                     <l>Of funerall Dogs, and warnings of ſad Owles.</l>
                     <l>The Taſt diſtaſteth all things, and the ſame</l>
                     <l>Is ſweet, and bitter, when the inward flame</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:26"/>Furres the ſwolne Tongue; &amp; the quick Feeling marr'd,</l>
                     <l>Knoweth no difference betweene ſoft and hard:</l>
                     <l>Such a confuſed Error doth diſtract</l>
                     <l>The labouring Senſes, ſo is the Fancie rackt</l>
                     <l>By the dire ſickneſſe; when from place to place</l>
                     <l>The Bodie rolleth, and would faine embrace</l>
                     <l>Some Icie cooler: but alas, the heat</l>
                     <l>Aſſwaging, there enſues a Marble ſweat</l>
                     <l>'Twixt Death and Nature, wreſtling: then appeare</l>
                     <l>Thoſe deadly Characters, which th'Enſigne beare</l>
                     <l>Before approching Fate; which notice give,</l>
                     <l>None ſpotleſſe die, how ever they did live.</l>
                     <l>A ſickneſſe comfortleſſe; when we do feare</l>
                     <l>To ſee thoſe friends whom we do love moſt deare.</l>
                     <l>The Miniſters Devotion here doth ſtick,</l>
                     <l>By leaving Viſitation of the ſick,</l>
                     <l>Making the Service-Booke imperfect: when</l>
                     <l>We ſee a croſſed Doore, as 'twere a Den</l>
                     <l>Of Serpents, or a Prodigie, we ſhun</l>
                     <l>The poore diſtreſſed Habitation.</l>
                     <l>The Death as comfortleſſe; where not appeares</l>
                     <l>One friend, to ſhed ſome tender funerall teares:</l>
                     <l>Black Night's the onely Mourner. No ſad Verſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſolemne flowers do deck the drearie Herſe:</l>
                     <l>Some few old folke perhaps, for many a yeere</l>
                     <l>Who have forgot to weepe, attend the Beere;</l>
                     <l>Such, whoſe drie age hath made moſt fit to keepe</l>
                     <l>Th'infected without feare, but not to weepe;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe kin to death, made them not feare to die,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe deafeneſſe made them then fit companie</l>
                     <l>Vnto the ſick, when they were ſpeechleſſe growne:</l>
                     <l>A miſerable Conſolation.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:27"/>But had you look'd about, you might have ſeene</l>
                     <l>Death in each corner, and the ſecret teene</l>
                     <l>Of angrie Deſtinie: No ſport diſpells</l>
                     <l>The miſts of ſorrow; a ſad ſilence dwells</l>
                     <l>In all the ſtreets, and a pale terror ſeizes</l>
                     <l>Vpon their faces, who had no Diſeaſes.</l>
                     <l>So uſuall 'twas, before the Morne to die,</l>
                     <l>That when at Night two friends left companie,</l>
                     <l>They would not ſay, <hi>Good Night</hi>; but thus alone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God ſend's a ioyfull Reſurrection.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If two or three dayes interpos'd betweene,</l>
                     <l>One friend by chance another friend had ſeene,</l>
                     <l>It was as ſtrange, and joyfull, as to ſome,</l>
                     <l>When a deare friend doth from the <hi>Indies</hi> come.</l>
                     <l>Throgh the nak'd town, of death there was ſuch plenty,</l>
                     <l>One Bell at once was faine to ring for twenty.</l>
                     <l>No Clocks were heard to ſtrike upon their Bells,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe nothing rung but death-lamenting Knells.</l>
                     <l>Strange, that the Houres ſhould faile to tell the Day,</l>
                     <l>When Time to thouſands ran ſo faſt away.</l>
                     <l>Time was confus'd, and kept at ſuch a plight,</l>
                     <l>The Day to thouſands now was made a Night.</l>
                     <l>Hundreds that never ſaw before, but di'de,</l>
                     <l>At one ſame time, in one ſame Grave abide;</l>
                     <l>That our weake Fancies, if we did not hold</l>
                     <l>It Profanation, here to be too bold,</l>
                     <l>Might wonder what, being ſtrangers, they would ſay</l>
                     <l>To one another at the Iudgement Day.</l>
                     <l>Some, by their feare to go to Church debarr'd,</l>
                     <l>Anon are carryed dead unto the Yard.</l>
                     <l>The Church-yards gron'd, with too much death op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt,</l>
                     <l>And the Earth reſts not, 'cauſe ſo many reſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:27"/>And Churches now with too much buriall fed,</l>
                     <l>Fear'd they ſhould haue no meetings but of Dead:</l>
                     <l>Death fell on death, and men began to feare</l>
                     <l>That men would want to carry forth the Bere.</l>
                     <l>The Bearers, Keepers, Sextons that remaine</l>
                     <l>Surpaſſe in number all the towne againe.</l>
                     <l>Friends here kill'd friends, womb-fellowes Kill their Brothers</l>
                     <l>Fathers their Sons, and Daughters kill their Mothers:</l>
                     <l>By one another (ſtrange!) ſo many di'de</l>
                     <l>And yet no murder here, no Homicide.</l>
                     <l>A Mother great with Child by the Plagues might</l>
                     <l>Infects to Death her Child not borne to light.</l>
                     <l>So killing that which yet ne're liu'd; the wombe</l>
                     <l>Of th'aliue Mother, to th'dead Child was tombe,</l>
                     <l>Where in the fleſhy graue the ſtill Babe lying</l>
                     <l>Doth kill his Mother by his owne firſt dying.</l>
                     <l>Her trauaile here on Earth ſhe could not tend</l>
                     <l>But finiſhes in heauen her Iournies end.</l>
                     <l>To others, frolicke ſet vnto their meales</l>
                     <l>Secure of death ſlie Death vpon them ſteales</l>
                     <l>And ſtrikes among 'em, ſo that thence in ſpeed</l>
                     <l>With heauy Cheere th'are borne the wormes to feed.</l>
                     <l>To ſome at worke to others at their play,</l>
                     <l>To thouſands death makes a long Holy-day.</l>
                     <l>Death all conditions equally inuades,</l>
                     <l>Nor riches, power, nor beautie here perſwades,</l>
                     <l>Old dye with young, with women men, the rage</l>
                     <l>Of the dire Plague ſpares neither ſex nor age.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Moſt powerfull Influence of ruling Starres</l>
                     <l>Which with blind darts Kill more than bloody Wars</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:28"/>Reſiſtleſſe Famine greedy Time, or when</l>
                     <l>The threatfull hand of Tyrants ſtriketh men</l>
                     <l>Into pale terrour, more than all diſeaſes</l>
                     <l>Ah, happy hee who heauen leaſt diſpleaſes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:28"/>
                  <p>HOLLAND <hi>his Hornet To ſting a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arlet:</hi> OR, A few Satyricall laſhes for one that did falſly accuſe him, to the late Lord Keeper, of a Libell againſt IOHN OVVENS Monument in <hi>Pauls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By ABRAHAM HOLLAND.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:29"/>
                  <head>Against one that impos'd a Libell on me, to the late Lord KEEPER.</head>
                  <l>WHoſoe're thou waſt that thus</l>
                  <l>Miſtaken or Malicious,</l>
                  <l>(The laſt I doe imagine) that</l>
                  <l>Didſt Father on mee this vile Brat</l>
                  <l>A ſtinking Libell, goe and bee</l>
                  <l>Scorn'd of all as much as mee.</l>
                  <l>May I know thy Name in Time</l>
                  <l>Libell'd in ſome Ballad-Rime:</l>
                  <l>May I heare thee 'bout the Street</l>
                  <l>Begging Offall for the <hi>Fleet</hi>:</l>
                  <l>May'ſt thou cry in tuned Proſe</l>
                  <l>Cornes haue you on your Feet, or Toes,</l>
                  <l>Or Rats to catch, and in the end</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veniee</hi>-Glaſſes haue you to mend.</l>
                  <l>May Iuſtice make thee ſo to lacke</l>
                  <l>To offer Lines to all in Blacke.</l>
                  <l>And ſucceed if Vengeance linger</l>
                  <l>At laſt the one-Legg'd Ballad-Singer.</l>
                  <l>Foule ill thy judgement, couldſt thou find</l>
                  <l>None whom thou couldſt thinke inclin'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:30"/>To Libelling but me, no one</l>
                  <l>That made lewd Verſe but me alone.</l>
                  <l>No itching Scriuener that doth make</l>
                  <l>Verſes by an Almanacke?</l>
                  <l>No lazie leaden-witted, Aſſe</l>
                  <l>Profeſſing Poetrie (alas.)</l>
                  <l>No Latin'd Merchant, whoſe fine clothes</l>
                  <l>Scorne that hee ſhould write in Proſe?</l>
                  <l>No parcell-Gentleman that vowes</l>
                  <l>Hee can ſtill the Latine towze?</l>
                  <l>No buſie Lawyers Clerke, that ſtill</l>
                  <l>Will vſurpe Poeticke skill?</l>
                  <l>No pretie Toy, no learned Foole?</l>
                  <l>Nor clowniſh <hi>Vſher of a Schoole</hi>?</l>
                  <l>Couldſt thou find none, but muſt diſperſe</l>
                  <l>Mee the Author of that Verſe</l>
                  <l>So baſely libellous, and durſt</l>
                  <l>Me of all men picke out firſt</l>
                  <l>To bee thy Toung-Ball? or didſt rather</l>
                  <l>Thy owne baſtard on mee Father?</l>
                  <l>A Palſey take my Muſe, if I</l>
                  <l>Knew how to make a quicke reply</l>
                  <l>To them who did this Fame diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>Whether it were Verſe or Proſe,</l>
                  <l>A Volume, or a Pamphlet, long</l>
                  <l>Or ſhort, Iämbick, or a ſong</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Latine,</hi> or <hi>Greeke, Tuſcan,</hi> or <hi>Welch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or ſuch as puffing <hi>Dutchmen</hi> belch</l>
                  <l>In their Fat Language: ſtrange that I</l>
                  <l>Should ſtretch a Line from <hi>Coventry</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And make it reach to <hi>Pauls,</hi> and place</l>
                  <l>It under OVVENS <hi>brazen face:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:30"/>Wretch! I would haue thee know, that Time</l>
                  <l>I was vers'd in other Rime</l>
                  <l>As free from malice, as from thee</l>
                  <l>And the wrong thou putſt on mee:</l>
                  <l>Where ſweet Damſels did infuſe</l>
                  <l>Flame into mee, and to my Muſe,</l>
                  <l>The onely ſting I had did riſe</l>
                  <l>From the Luſtre of their eyes,</l>
                  <l>Where our Paſtime was, to ſing</l>
                  <l>By the Bankes of ſome cleare Spring:</l>
                  <l>No venome ambuſh'd in thoſe Floods</l>
                  <l>Which haue no Satyres in our Woods</l>
                  <l>Onely ſometime in gentle Rankes</l>
                  <l>As wee walked o're the Bankes</l>
                  <l>I a blacke-ſwolne Toade did ſee</l>
                  <l>Wee now I thinke was kin to thee:</l>
                  <l>But of a better kinde, that could</l>
                  <l>Within it ſelfe it's venome hold.</l>
                  <l>Well, thou haſt done thy worſt to mee,</l>
                  <l>I'le tell thee what I thinke of thee,</l>
                  <l>Sure ſome opinionated Aſſe</l>
                  <l>Thou art, who in the world doſt paſſe</l>
                  <l>For a wiſe Man (by theſe rules</l>
                  <l>Wee beſt know who are beſt Fooles)</l>
                  <l>Some boſome-creeper, fed with ſloth,</l>
                  <l>A Foole, a Mad-man, or elſe both:</l>
                  <l>Some ſeeming Statiſt, who canſt find</l>
                  <l>By what's before, what is behind.</l>
                  <l>That hadſt as much reſpect of mee</l>
                  <l>As I meane to haue of thee.</l>
                  <l>Yea, this I gueſſe, and certaine know it</l>
                  <l>Thou art held ſome <note n="*" place="margin">Or if yo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> will <hi>Errant<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>arrant</hi> Poet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>One of thoſe about the Towne</l>
                  <l>Who did ſcatter up and downe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Naenia's</hi> on th'untimely Fate</l>
                  <l>Of the good Duke, and DORSET late.</l>
                  <l>Who in nought more luckleſſe were</l>
                  <l>Than that They left thee tampring here</l>
                  <l>To ſoyle their Ghoſts, and whiter Fames</l>
                  <l>And lamentably teare their Names.</l>
                  <l>Some Fantaſticke Cockeſ-combe, who</l>
                  <l>Affects a garbe with much adoe.</l>
                  <l>Yea, though perhaps thou bear'ſt my Name,</l>
                  <l>At thy conditions I <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhame:</l>
                  <l>And this I'le lay my life vpon</l>
                  <l>None of my Religion,</l>
                  <l>Who as haply 'tis thy vſe</l>
                  <l>Would'ſt the People thus ſeduce</l>
                  <l>And Malicious draw on mee</l>
                  <l>A crime ſo neere to Hereſie</l>
                  <l>That is to wrong my friends, and made</l>
                  <l>Mee this vncouth ſtile inuade</l>
                  <l>To bee a rayler, who doe vſe,</l>
                  <l>The world doth know, a gentler Muſe.</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:31"/>
                  <head>TO MY DEARE FATHER, Mr. <hi>PHILEMON HOLLAND,</hi> Doctor in Phyſicke, beeing Sicke.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SPring</hi> of my life, by whom I firſt did trie</l>
                  <l>This bitter-ſweet of fraile Mortalitie:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Source</hi> of my beeing, next to him that giues</l>
                  <l>The diuine Power, by which each mortall liues:</l>
                  <l>O thinke not but your Children doe comprize</l>
                  <l>Part of your Sickneſſe, wee all ſympathize</l>
                  <l>In your Diſeaſe: let it to all bee knowne</l>
                  <l>What e're is yours in ſorrow, is mine owne.</l>
                  <l>Let no <hi>ill Omen</hi> bee that while I write</l>
                  <l>To yeeld ſome comfort, teares doe blind my ſight,</l>
                  <l>I would ſuppreſſe'em; nor vaine-glorious hence</l>
                  <l>Seeke other witneſſe but my Conſcience</l>
                  <l>Which may to GOD beare record, how my heart,</l>
                  <l>In each diſaſter, with you beares a part.</l>
                  <l>Let me, deare Father, pardon here implore</l>
                  <l>If my Muſe languiſh; ne're had I before</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>So ill a Theame: the Subiect dimm's mine eyes</l>
                  <l>And makes my ſickly Verſes ſympathize.</l>
                  <l>O, how my hautie Muſe I could haue ſtrain'd</l>
                  <l>If I had ſeene your merits had obtayn'd</l>
                  <l>A due reward: if I had knowne the worth</l>
                  <l>Which lyes in you had bin full blazed forth</l>
                  <l>About the world; and ſo might gladly ſee</l>
                  <l>Your worthy name as deare to all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as mee.</l>
                  <l>And now, good Father, as I know your mind</l>
                  <l>Is with all precepts drawne from Heauen refin'd</l>
                  <l>Though Sickneſſe bee the calling for the Skore</l>
                  <l>The Epitome, and Bill of life before</l>
                  <l>By which as by a Serjeant God demands</l>
                  <l>Of paſſed life defrayment at our hands:</l>
                  <l>Yet let not us a Medicine applie</l>
                  <l>To one ſo fraught with good Phyloſophie,</l>
                  <l>But let us them of you ſtill borrow, giuing</l>
                  <l>By liuing ſtill, example of good liuing.</l>
                  <l>Yet if a young unſtayed head may giue</l>
                  <l>Precepts to die (when Fate doth pleaſe) and liue,</l>
                  <l>(Long may it bee) 'tis thus: O, let not cares</l>
                  <l>That gall the troubled mind, nor ſad affaires</l>
                  <l>Of this world vexe you, neither thinke it loſſe</l>
                  <l>If to gaine <hi>Heaven,</hi> you gaine but little <hi>droſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of fading wealth; I dare without ſinne ſweare</l>
                  <l>That wealth's unworthy you, that's ſcraped here.</l>
                  <l>Let it not grieue you that the <hi>vulgar crew</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Haue not to your deſeruings giuen the dew;</l>
                  <l>Vertue moſt part is in the world deſpiz'd</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that moſt doe merit leaſt are priz'd.</l>
                  <l>You know that ſo it hath bin in all Ages,</l>
                  <l>The beſt Philoſophers, and wiſeſt Sages,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:32"/>The greateſt Poets haue bin ſtill exempt</l>
                  <l>Of preſent glory, drowned in contempt,</l>
                  <l>When yet their glorious Fame that could not die</l>
                  <l>Was crown'd with future immortalitie.</l>
                  <l>God is in debt to them who here haue liu'd</l>
                  <l>Deſeruing well, and little haue receiu'd,</l>
                  <l>And though the Principall a while doe reſt</l>
                  <l>Hee'l pay't at laſt with double intereſt,</l>
                  <l>Heauen is not rich for nothing, but be ſure</l>
                  <l>'Tis treaſur'd for the wealth-deſeruing Poore.</l>
                  <l>And to your ſelfe though God defray not it</l>
                  <l>Your Childrens children ſhall receiue it yet.</l>
                  <l>I would not haue you enuie them, who here</l>
                  <l>In the worlds judgement glorious appeare,</l>
                  <l>On whom this Earth's abounding wealth encroaches</l>
                  <l>Who liue ſecure, whoſe Heauen is their Coaches,</l>
                  <l>Long traines of Seruants, and delicious cates,</l>
                  <l>Saluters, Flatterers, and delicates</l>
                  <l>For their faire carkaſſes: beleeue it true</l>
                  <l>God's ſcarce acquainted with thus-bleſs'd a crew.</l>
                  <l>His owne <hi>Sonn</hi>'s an example, who among</l>
                  <l>Vs men, was poore, deſpiz'd, and ſuffer'd wrong,</l>
                  <l>To whom men ſcarce would meanes or meales afford;</l>
                  <l>O, who would grudge to imitate our Lord?</l>
                  <l>Yet know when blacke Obliuion ſhall rot</l>
                  <l>Their worthleſſe names, their merits flouriſh not,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall your memory unbounded flie</l>
                  <l>And neuer periſh till the world doe die.</l>
                  <l>O, doe not under-value ſo your ſelfe</l>
                  <l>To thinke them richer who haue greater pelfe,</l>
                  <l>I'le undertake ten thouſand in this Land</l>
                  <l>Who both themſelues and you doe underſtand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:33"/>Though cloy'd with riches on their wealthy floores</l>
                  <l>Would willingly exchange their worth for yours.</l>
                  <l>O! that I could perſwade you to thinke leſſe</l>
                  <l>Of this baſe world, and ſee your happineſſe.</l>
                  <l>Say, this ungratefull Towne, this luckleſſe Cage</l>
                  <l>Wherein you haue bin cooped all your age</l>
                  <l>And ſpent your golden yeares, to gaine a few</l>
                  <l>Who are in nothing but diſſembling true</l>
                  <l>Hollow, tongue-friends, if I may call them friends</l>
                  <l>Who haue vs'd you to their peculiar ends</l>
                  <l>A friend in title, but a ſlaue indeed</l>
                  <l>To ſerue their turnes: ô that you had tane heed</l>
                  <l>In time of theſe: yet what ſhould one expect</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a baſe-borne rabble but neglect</l>
                  <l>For good deſerts: a rout that neuer knew</l>
                  <l>What meant moralitie, nor euer drew</l>
                  <l>The Sacred milke of Learning: whoſe chiefe height</l>
                  <l>Is to know yards of Draperie, and the weight</l>
                  <l>Of Grocerie and Spices, whoſe baſe birth</l>
                  <l>Life, manners, friendſhip, all doe ſmell of earth</l>
                  <l>Groſſe vile and muddie: yet one comfort is</l>
                  <l>The time may bee when you this Towne ſhall miſſe</l>
                  <l>And ſay with griefe, we once had ſuch a one</l>
                  <l>Wee hated vertue preſent, but now gone</l>
                  <l>We long and wiſh for't. Thus in many places</l>
                  <l>The worthieſt mens rewards haue bin diſgraces;</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Athens</hi> wont her beſt deſeruers uſe</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Rome</hi> her noble Stateſmen to abuſe</l>
                  <l>With death or baniſhment: thus ſtill wee trie</l>
                  <l>Contempt enſues familiaritie:</l>
                  <l>Yea, Prophets (as our Sauiours ſelfe did deeme)</l>
                  <l>In their owne Countries ſtill haue ſmall eſteeme.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:33"/>Well, whatſoe're this Towne doe thinke you, let</l>
                  <l>It thus bee Knowne, All <hi>England</hi>'s in your debt.</l>
                  <l>Yet are there ſome (I dare avouch it) good</l>
                  <l>Ingenuous mindes who hauing underſtood</l>
                  <l>Your worth and merits, loue your very <hi>name,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though farre remote, yea, and admire the ſame.</l>
                  <l>I doubt not yet, deare Father, e're you die</l>
                  <l>By timely Fate, to ſee you rais'd as high</l>
                  <l>As your well-weigh'd ambition aimes at, which</l>
                  <l>Is to bee ſweetly well content, not rich,</l>
                  <l>T'enioy your friends, and children, and they you</l>
                  <l>To ſpend your fading old yeares reſidue</l>
                  <l>In ſweet tranquillitie, and liue with ſuch</l>
                  <l>As will reſpect and honour you as much</l>
                  <l>As here they ſlight you, and the time from hence</l>
                  <l>Shall all your paſt misfortunes recompence:</l>
                  <l>All comforts fit for age ſhall you be giuen,</l>
                  <l>Your onely care to make your path for Heauen.</l>
                  <l>And if my ſelfe a Poet may preſage</l>
                  <l>You ſhall haue yet an old new Golden age.</l>
                  <l>God will not end your aged dayes, ſo long</l>
                  <l>As you may ſtill helpe and doe good among</l>
                  <l>His people here: But as a Captaine when</l>
                  <l>He meanes to exerciſe his faithfull'ſt men</l>
                  <l>He puts them upon dangers, makes them trie</l>
                  <l>Diſaſters, hardneſſe and all miſerie,</l>
                  <l>That when at laſt the foe ſhall be repair'd</l>
                  <l>They bee not found unskill'd and unprepar'd.</l>
                  <l>Sickneſſe is but a muſtring ſhow, wherein</l>
                  <l>Wee learne to fight, to skirmiſh and to win</l>
                  <l>At the laſt combat, Death: in that tide</l>
                  <l>Happy is hee that ofteſt Sickneſſe tride.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:34"/>Such as did all-wayes in full health remaine</l>
                  <l>Are oft poore wretches lamentably ſlaine</l>
                  <l>As untri'd Souldiers. Though once Fate by God</l>
                  <l>Shall of your fraile make a period.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>To his Friends in the Time of his Sickneſſe.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A reſolution against Death.</head>
                  <l>FRiends, if it bee my lot, as ſome men vſe</l>
                  <l>To pay their debt ſooner than you would chuſe</l>
                  <l>To harſh exacting Fate I would not haue</l>
                  <l>You ſtand lamenting o're my youthfull Graue</l>
                  <l>As if it were my Priſon, and I throwne</l>
                  <l>There on a deſperate Execution.</l>
                  <l>I know there's no releaſe from't yet more free</l>
                  <l>Know I this priſon than your libertie.</l>
                  <l>I would not haue you raile at it, and ſay</l>
                  <l>That it from you had cloſely ſtolne away</l>
                  <l>And treacherouſly betray'd your Friend: alas</l>
                  <l>They erre who thinke they into th'graue doe paſſe</l>
                  <l>As to a Puniſhment, and therefore call</l>
                  <l>It the ſad Vrne, the Place of Buriall,</l>
                  <l>The houſe of Lamentation, Lifes Thiefe;</l>
                  <l>The Den of Sorrow, and the Cell of Griefe:</l>
                  <l>You wrong it by theſe Names, It is my Bed,</l>
                  <l>Where Lifes Day ſpent, I lay my wearied</l>
                  <l>And o'retoyl'd Body, in a long deepe Night</l>
                  <l>Till hee that giues all Day, renew my Light.</l>
                  <l>It is my ſleeping chayre, my chayre of State,</l>
                  <l>Wherein I ſit equall with conquering Fate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:35"/>And out-face Death, daring him if hee can</l>
                  <l>To challenge more than I haue payd of Man.</l>
                  <l>Make him my Sinnes-bill cancell, and agree</l>
                  <l>That Chriſts croſſe o're it my acquittance bee.</l>
                  <l>As a poore Traueller, whom the conceite</l>
                  <l>Of a long tedious Iourney, thitſt, and heate,</l>
                  <l>And wearineſſe tormenteth, by the Way</l>
                  <l>Longing for home, all he can doe, doth Pray</l>
                  <l>For ſome Refreſhment, at the laſt eſpies</l>
                  <l>The joyfull ſmoake of his owne Countrey riſe</l>
                  <l>To bid him welcome: then with Pleaſures Teares</l>
                  <l>Hee caſts away both Languiſhment, and Feares.</l>
                  <l>And ſmiling takes the next Banke hee doth ſee.</l>
                  <l>So pleaſing is my Graue, ſo ſweet to mee.</l>
                  <l>This piece of Ground, which you in ſcorne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance</l>
                  <l>Miſcall my Graue, is my Inheritance.</l>
                  <l>That 'tis intayl'd on me, the Law averres</l>
                  <l>By due ſucceſſion from my Grandfathers.</l>
                  <l>Mine it hath bin, by right, ſince <hi>Adam</hi> curſt</l>
                  <l>Man with this Bleſſing, and poſſeſs'd it firſt.</l>
                  <l>While I haue Life heere, I am but Lifes Ward;</l>
                  <l>And by my Nonage from my right debarr'd.</l>
                  <l>Death giues me that's ſo long kept from my Hand</l>
                  <l>I'me now at Age, and come unto my Land.</l>
                  <l>Nor thinke my Purchaſe too ſoone gayn'd, but call</l>
                  <l>My eight and twentie Climactericall.</l>
                  <l>My Graue's my long-ſought Inne to which at moſt</l>
                  <l>It can be ſaid, that I haue ridden Poſt.</l>
                  <l>Whither retyred ſome perhaps will feare</l>
                  <l>The ſawcie Wormes will bee intruders there</l>
                  <l>To feed upon me, whileſt my Faith proteſts</l>
                  <l>It is not ſo, they bee my bidden Gueſts.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:35"/>What Man is hee, that hauing in the Time</l>
                  <l>Of life, committed ſome foule haynous crime.</l>
                  <l>And knowing that the Fame of it's inroll'd</l>
                  <l>In characters of Braſſe, yea were't of Gold,</l>
                  <l>That would not praiſe the hand, and friendly call</l>
                  <l>Which ſcratches out the ſad Memoriall</l>
                  <l>Wherein doth liue his Infamie: what ſoule</l>
                  <l>That knowes this fleſhly Table doth inroll</l>
                  <l>The Memory of our Faults, that would not call</l>
                  <l>Wormes and the Graue Redreſſers of our Fall.</l>
                  <l>The one of which doth hide, the other devoures</l>
                  <l>All that was guiltie, ſhamefull, bad of ours.</l>
                  <l>Our Graue's the veyle, which ſhadowes from the eyes</l>
                  <l>Of Poſthume Malice our Iniquities.</l>
                  <l>This wretched thing you mourne for and behold</l>
                  <l>The dreary Linnen, and the Earth to fold.</l>
                  <l>This thing compact of ſinewes, Bone and Blood</l>
                  <l>The Receptacle both of Sinne, and Food</l>
                  <l>Death's ready Executioners, This</l>
                  <l>This is not <hi>Holland,</hi> but's Effigies</l>
                  <l>Which when 'twas beſt, and by the Soule could moue</l>
                  <l>Was but a liuely ſhape of God aboue</l>
                  <l>And onely bleſs'd in that, but now, alas!</l>
                  <l>That chiefe Ingredient of the curious Maſſe</l>
                  <l>That gaue it Actiue Life is ta'ne away</l>
                  <l>And Nothing left but ruine, and Decay:</l>
                  <l>A thing ſo deſpicable, baſe, and vile</l>
                  <l>That leſt it ſhould ſurviving Men defile</l>
                  <l>Wee Priſon'<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> firſt in Linnen, then in Wood</l>
                  <l>Then ramme it deepe in Earth, and to make Good</l>
                  <l>The reſt, leſt it againe approach the Day</l>
                  <l>Make marble Bulwarkes o're the wretched clay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:36"/>
                     <hi>Egyptians</hi> hence did their dead Kings embowre</l>
                  <l>In tombes as bigge as their blaſpheming Towre.</l>
                  <l>Raiſing in weaker mindes ſometimes a doubt</l>
                  <l>How they at th'Reſurrection will get out.</l>
                  <l>Of theſe ſtrong Priſons, whoſe unweldy Frames</l>
                  <l>Seeme rather to oppreſſe, than raiſe their Names.</l>
                  <l>Doubtleſs this wretched thing call'd Man whoſe curſe</l>
                  <l>Light upon all things, is than all things worſe</l>
                  <l>When once his ſoule is gone; The ſilly Flower</l>
                  <l>Though dead, and wither'd, yet retaines ſome Power</l>
                  <l>Availeable in Phyſicke; Cattell when</l>
                  <l>Th'are dead themſelues, nouriſh the liues of Men</l>
                  <l>And dead Graſſe theirs; And Corne is neuer good</l>
                  <l>Vntill it bee cut downe, and us'd for food.</l>
                  <l>No tree ſo rude, no ſhrub ſo baſe, no beaſt</l>
                  <l>So vile, but dead ſerues for ſome uſe, at leaſt</l>
                  <l>For ornament, wee loue to ſee by skill</l>
                  <l>A curious limb'd Picture, and ſtand ſtill</l>
                  <l>To gaze upon it, yea wee can endure</l>
                  <l>To ſee Deaths ſhaddow, and grim Portraicture</l>
                  <l>Though ne're ſo ugly, when againſt a wall</l>
                  <l>Set a dead man indeed, amongſt us all</l>
                  <l>You ſcarcely ſhall finde one that will not flie</l>
                  <l>As at a Monſter or grim Prodigie.</l>
                  <l>Doe you then grieue to ſee this Bugbeare toy</l>
                  <l>This ſcarre-crow layd aſide, to ſhun th'annoy</l>
                  <l>Of the beholders? or for my Soule is it</l>
                  <l>That you doe mourne, which now doe throned ſit</l>
                  <l>Surfetting with pure Ioyes, and holy mirth</l>
                  <l>And ſmiles at that for which you weepe on earth</l>
                  <l>That 'tis diſlodg'd from that debauched Inne</l>
                  <l>Which helpt it ne're in ought, but onely ſinne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:36"/>I would haue giuen you leaue to mourne if then</l>
                  <l>I had by ſuddaine Death, bin ſummon'd, when</l>
                  <l>Wretch'd man I labour'd to the height of ſin</l>
                  <l>And bolder grew the deeper I grew in;</l>
                  <l>When Vice was turn'd to cuſtome, and each deed</l>
                  <l>Though ne're ſo impious, did perſwade with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Another worſe, as if Deſpaire had bin</l>
                  <l>The beaſtly Pander to unbrideled ſin.</l>
                  <l>But Heau'n be bleſs'd, Heau'n better lou'd my ſoule</l>
                  <l>Than without ſtay to let it headlong roll</l>
                  <l>To everlaſting Death, and ſo did Kill</l>
                  <l>The Body ſooner to retayne that ſtill.</l>
                  <l>The Soule as hee inſpir'd it pure, nor at all</l>
                  <l>Conſcious of ſinne, no not Originall.</l>
                  <l>Thinke you I feare thoſe things which you doe call</l>
                  <l>By ſuch blacke names? The Griefly Funerall</l>
                  <l>The Fatall beere, ſad Flowers and dreary Hearſe</l>
                  <l>The mournefull Followers, and the weeping Verſe?</l>
                  <l>Thinke you already I doe not diſdaine</l>
                  <l>The mightie tapers, and the ſable traine?</l>
                  <l>Or e're I doe expire, thinke you my ſoule</l>
                  <l>Will be ſo cowardly, to feare the toll</l>
                  <l>Of a ſad bell, whoſe heauy language goes</l>
                  <l>Deadly as if it did intend to cloſe</l>
                  <l>It's voyce with mine? Thinke you I doe not ſpie</l>
                  <l>The dolefull ſilence of the ſtanders by</l>
                  <l>As if they all were ſpeechleſſe, and from me</l>
                  <l>Did draw one generall ſtupid ſympathy?</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes I heare the ſilly Women ſay</l>
                  <l>Hee is whole cheſted, and will goe away</l>
                  <l>By dying upward, and ſome other trie</l>
                  <l>If that my legges be cold, and ſtraight doe lye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:37"/>Heres one doth Iudge my feeble Pulſe, and cryes</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe ſhee muſt bee the Friend to cloſe mine eyes.</l>
                  <l>Another maketh Triall of my Breath</l>
                  <l>Thus doe I heare 'em furniſh me for Death.</l>
                  <l>But ó let me not heare them, let my ſprite</l>
                  <l>Bee buſie then in purchaſing a light:</l>
                  <l>More ſweet then Life it ſelfe, may wholly I</l>
                  <l>Bee fix'd in thoughts of Immortalitie.</l>
                  <l>Let me then an audacious Client ſtand</l>
                  <l>Preſſing to Kiſſe my unſeene Sauiours hand,</l>
                  <l>And let me bee ſo buſie in my Prayers</l>
                  <l>That not the Feare of Death, nor ougly cares</l>
                  <l>Throng'd in the memory may diſturbe the Soule</l>
                  <l>Which now is neere to Heav'n her capitoll</l>
                  <l>In the laſt Triumph, after Conqueſt wonne</l>
                  <l>O're Death and Hell; and grim Perdition.</l>
                  <l>Tis a toy to thinke when life is paſt</l>
                  <l>That Fate did lagge, or elſe made too much haſt</l>
                  <l>When wee die quickly, or by tedious Age</l>
                  <l>Fulfill the circuit of Lifes Pilgrimage</l>
                  <l>In my opinion a Day-ag'd Child</l>
                  <l>Hath when it dyes a race as well fulfill'd</l>
                  <l>As Clymacterick Old men; I confeſſe</l>
                  <l>Not with ſo many out-rodes, yet no leſſe</l>
                  <l>Exactly. Nature doth averre the ſame</l>
                  <l>And a day Roſe, aſwell an Age may claime</l>
                  <l>As the long liued Oake: Though Time devoure</l>
                  <l>The one ſo ſlowly th'other in an Houre.</l>
                  <l>If'cauſe I dye before you, you repine</l>
                  <l>I'le thinke you enuy at this bliſſe of mine</l>
                  <l>And wiſh't your owne, there's nought but ſinne in me</l>
                  <l>That could deſerue long life, and miſerie:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:37"/>Which Sinne, the God of Mercy quell'd, and check't</l>
                  <l>The cauſe, and after tooke away th'effect</l>
                  <l>Long life; or if becauſe I dye ſo ſoone</l>
                  <l>And come into mine Evening at the Noone</l>
                  <l>And full Meridian of mine age, you erre</l>
                  <l>And doe not know what bliſſe the Fates conferre</l>
                  <l>On mee hereby, by which I ſhall obtayne</l>
                  <l>As I now dye to riſe at laſt againe</l>
                  <l>In freſher youth: The Marriner behold</l>
                  <l>To gather up a little Pelfe and Gold</l>
                  <l>Contemned Death; If hee doe chance to finde</l>
                  <l>A nearer Cut to <hi>China,</hi> or to <hi>Inde</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reioyceth, and ſhall wee who through this vale</l>
                  <l>And gulfe of miſerie in Life doe ſayle,</l>
                  <l>Grudge if the Fates doe ſhow a nearer Haven,</l>
                  <l>Our Purchaſe being no Gold nor Pelfe but Heaven?</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:38"/>
                  <head>A LETTER, Savouring of Mortification, written and ſent in the time of the late Viſitation of the Plague, to his deere Brother <hi>H. H.</hi> in LONDON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare Brother,</hi> I am ſorry your other occaſions would not permit mee to enjoy your company longer, at my laſt being at <hi>London</hi>; eſpecially, in this time of ſorrow, when the deareſt friends are not able to ſay to day, wee will meet to morrow: which me thinkes cannot chooſe but put e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man in minde how carefull hee ought to bee, that though in our Kinred and Friendſhip wee be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on Earth, wee may by true repentance, and relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing our ſinnes, gaine that bliſſe that at the reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againe of ſoule and body, in that happy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:14511:39"/>
of Saints we may meet againe with joy. Our ſmall Village here as an out-member of your great Citie ſuffers proportionably with it the heauy ſtroke of Gods wrath, inſomuch that whole Families of the moſt curious preventers haue beene wofully ſwept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: eſpecially a Gentleman leſt to keepe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Nottinghams</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">This houſe is called, the Kings Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie.</note> Houſe, who with his Wife a beautifull Gentlewoman, and foure moſt ſweet and louely Children, and their Man, are all gone, I hope to bliſſe, and their Mayd that is onely left, lying at the mercy of God: Wretch that I am, why delay I one minute, to caſt my ſelfe proſtrate at the feet of Mercy, and prepare my ſelfe for the like paſſage? Within theſe few dayes moſt of this houſe in the judgement of men were likely to out-liue mee, whoſe wilde and looſer youth threatens a too timely old-age: They liu'd in a beautious Houſe, a refined and pure Ayre, wanted neither Antidote nor aſſiſting Phyſicke, and yet alas they now are not, they are duſt, and aſhes, and the food of Wormes. O! the depth of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our great GOD: hee ſaw that it was good for them to dye to gaine a better life, and for us, that by their deaths wee may learne and prepare our ſelues to dye. Ah Brother! thinke not this is a time Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically to ſet forth a ſorrow, or paſſion, thinke not but my heart ſpeakes what I write; I know the reward of Sinne, I know the value of a Soule, thinke not but while it is in my power, by the merits of CHRIST, I will haue a care and prouidence for the price of my Saviours blood, my Soule.</p>
                  <p>Deare Brother, I doubt not but you are ſo well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb facs="tcp:14511:39"/>
and armed againſt this Viſitation of God, that my weake devotion is either needleſſe, or unable to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt you: Yet I deſire you not any way to deject your ſelfe (onely in the humiliation for ſinne) in this great Aſſizes of Almighty God where we all are brought to our Trials. For my ſelfe I thanke the comforting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, I haue not beene theſe many yeares in ſo great ſecuritie as I am in this time of imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: When euery minute telling me I muſt die, and that God knowes how ſoone, I now and but now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to liue; alas the time that I ſpent before was but death, and I liu'd but in a dreame. A man in my judgement never more liues than when hee is moſt mortified; I perſwade my ſelfe that man ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer die who di'd while hee liu'd. Brother, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolu'd ſo ſoone as this heauy Storme is ouer to enter my ſelfe into the Orders of the Miniſtrie, wherein I doubt not but to finde ſuch Friends as quickly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide my ſelfe of an honeſt and competent liuing, God is my judge I ſhall not bee at quiet till by truely labouring to ſaue others Soules I aſſure mine owne ſaluation. If God lend me a longer life, this is my reſolution; if otherwiſe, it bee his will to take mee from hence, though I could not in my Life, I beſeech God that I may glorifie him in my Death. I pray you when you write to <hi>Coventry</hi> to remember my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt dutie to my deare and aged Parents, to whom I doubt not yet but by adding ſome comfort to their grey-hayres, to requite partly my former diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: deſire both them and my Brothers and Siſters to pray for mee, as I doe for them. Brother, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14511:40"/>
you haue beene more like a Father than a Brother unto mee; God bee with you, remember mee to your Wife, and let us heartily pray for one another and bee cheerefull. I reſt;</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your loving Brother: <hi>ABRAHAM HOLLAND.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Chelſey,</hi>
                        <date>Auguſt, 24. 1625.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="confession">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:40"/>
                  <head>A Confeſsion of my Sinnes to <hi>GOD,</hi> and a testimonie of my Faith.</head>
                  <p>TO number my ſinnes O Lord is impoſſible, for they haue bin infinite; to meaſure them our, paſt humane skill, for they haue bin im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe, and ah! too great: to repent truely for them not in my power, without the grace of thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: to obtaine pardon for them incredible, but through the infiniteneſſe of thy ſtill ready mercy, and the all-ſufficient-merits of my deare Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: yet (ô good Lord) were my ſinnes number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as the Sands, or Atomes that flit through the ayre; yet ſhould they neuer compare in number with thy Mercies; were they for quantitie not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, thy goodneſſe ſhould ſurpaſſe them: for qualitie not to bee mentioned, foule and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thy Pureneſſe is able to make them cleane, and turnes the blackeſt of them into whiteneſſe of Snow, their deepeſt graine of ſcarlet into wooll. I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I haue highly ſinned, (ô Lord) I haue long ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſhall ſtill ſinne unleſſe thou helpe (ô Lord) unleſſe thy grace prevent. To amend my life (ô Lord) I haue made many and earneſt vowes, when thou haſt but gently afflicted mee; in my health I haue ever ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped backe, and trodden in the ſteppes of my former
<pb facs="tcp:14511:41"/>
ſinnes, what then (ô Lord) can I expect but a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall miſerie that I may know thee? Yet (ô Lord) knowing that thy Will is not to deſtroy, but preſerue, thy Glory to forgiue, not puniſh, and my Saviour as willing as able to bee a powerfull Mediatour with thee, for us Sinners the price of his bitter Paſſion. In the name of it, in the name of thy Goodneſſe, thy Mercy, haue mercy good Lord upon mee, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire many drops of my Saviours blood to clenſe my Sinnes, ſo ſhall I praiſe thee <hi>in the Land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> before I goe into the Graue, and there bee no more remembrance of mee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>A Metricall Verſion of part of PSALME, 73.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SVre <hi>GOD</hi> loues Iſraell, and all</l>
                     <l>Whoſe hearts are cleane, yet I</l>
                     <l>Had like t'haue let my feet to fall</l>
                     <l>And trodden in iniquitie:</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I did the bad ungodly ſee</l>
                     <l>Stand ſtill and flouriſh in Proſperitie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>Death's perill they doe never feare,</l>
                     <l>But ſtrong and luſtie doe remaine:</l>
                     <l>Nor like to us misfortunes beare,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſuffer equall plagues and paine.</l>
                     <l>This is the cauſe that they are ſwolne with Pride</l>
                     <l>And over-whelm'd, in Crueltie abide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:41"/>
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>Their eyes with fatneſſe ſwell, and they</l>
                     <l>Doe whatſoe're they can deviſe</l>
                     <l>Others they doe Corrupt, and ſay</l>
                     <l>Moſt vile and wicked blaſphemies:</l>
                     <l>Nor ſticke they to revile the God of might</l>
                     <l>And againſt Heaven powre forth malicious ſpight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>Thus all the world they doe infect</l>
                     <l>Which makes the ſilly people goe</l>
                     <l>Aſide, and fall unto their Sect</l>
                     <l>Thinking that they are bleſſed ſo:</l>
                     <l>Tuſh how, ſay they, ſhall God perceiue what wee</l>
                     <l>Doe heere, ſhall hee from high our actions ſee?</l>
                     <l>&amp;c. &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Mr. <hi>T. C.</hi> the Authors endeared Friend his Poeticall Verſion on the <hi>91. PSALME.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <l>MAke the great God thy fort and dwell</l>
                     <l>In him, by Faith, and doe not care</l>
                     <l>(So ſhaded) for the fires of Hell</l>
                     <l>Nor for the cunning Fowlers ſnare</l>
                     <l>Nor Poyſon of th'infected Ayre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:42"/>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>His Plumes ſhall make a Downy bed</l>
                     <l>Where thou ſhalt reſt, hee ſhall diſplay</l>
                     <l>His wings of Truth over thy head</l>
                     <l>Which as a Shield ſhall chaſe away</l>
                     <l>The Dreads of Night, the Darts of Day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>The winged Plague that flies by night,</l>
                     <l>The Murdring Sword that kils by Day,</l>
                     <l>Shall not thy Peacefull ſleepes affright</l>
                     <l>Though, on thy right and left hand, they</l>
                     <l>A thouſand and tenne thouſand ſlay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>Onely thine eyes ſhall ſee the fall</l>
                     <l>Of Sinners; but becauſe thy Heart</l>
                     <l>Dwels with the Lord; not one of All</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Ills, nor yet the Plaguy dart</l>
                     <l>Shall dare approach neere where thou art.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <l>When thou art troubled hee ſhall heare</l>
                     <l>And helpe thee, for thy loue embrac't,</l>
                     <l>And knew his name; wherefore hee'le reare</l>
                     <l>Thy honours high; and when thou haſt</l>
                     <l>Enioy'd them long; ſaue thee at laſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>T. C.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:42"/>
                  <head>A MEDITATION ON, PSALM, 6. Verſ. 4.5.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Returne: deliver my Soule, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>ALL this Pſalme of DAVID is Prayer; and as one ſaid, the very dreames of the righteous bee prayers to GOD: So the very Songs of DAVID bee Prayers; In the beginning of the Pſalme he uſeth only a deprecatorie prayer, <hi>Rebuke me not, &amp;c.</hi> but afterwards hee comes to that Importunitie of prayer, that Impudency, that violence of prayer, as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith, When wee earneſtly Pray, <hi>Quaſi agimus facto Obſidemus Deum,</hi> and as the Mathematician ſaid, Hee could deuiſe an Inſtrument would remoue the whole fabricke of the world, if any one could but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe him a place where to ſettle it. So DAVID hauing as it were ſetled this great inſtrument of Prayer upon GOD, turnes and as it were ſteeres him which way he will. <hi>Returne:</hi> which implies that hee had bin there before, for as God firſt made Flowers and Trees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he made the Sunne, but after a Paradiſe when the Sunne did vivificate it; ſo God makes Man before the Sunne of Grace ſhine upon him, but then makes him a liuing Paradiſe, when hee inſpires the Sunne of righteouſneſſe into our Soules; and that is one kinde of returning to us; yea, when by many relapſes of ſin we fall from God, hee giues us againe grace to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that is another returning. There be three man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſignifications of the originall word <hi>Shuba,</hi> here
<pb facs="tcp:14511:43"/>
uſed. The firſt, <hi>Redire in locum ſuum,</hi> as heauy things to the Center and light to their exhauſion upward; ſo man returneth to the duſt from whence firſt he came; thus God returneth <hi>In terram ſuam,</hi> when hee reviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſoule of a ſinfull man. The ſecond, in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing his judgements from us. The third, when we by his corrections returne to him; as it ſaid <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> would haue returned in Sackcloth and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, where the ſame word <hi>Shuba</hi> in the Syriack tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is uſed. The ſecond, <hi>Eripe animam.</hi> The third, <hi>Salvum me ſac,</hi> which implies ſuch a Saluation as comes by CHRIST IESVS, the Originall beeing <hi>Iaſhag,</hi> whence IESVS comes.</p>
                  <p>The knowledge of God, is as <hi>Iob</hi> ſayes of his friends (to ſpeake with reuerence) a miſerable conſolation, without wee know him to bee our Saviour; the very Atheiſts though they would denie it, the Lord will by the terrours of night moue them to confeſſe there is a GOD; yea, they ſhall confeſſe there is a God, but ſhall not know him a Saviour.</p>
                  <p>It is ſtrange how in all the Old Teſtament the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients did abhorre, diſtaſt and pray againſt Death, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did know it was the way to their bliſſe; and indeed if we conſider death as it is, life and it may be put in an equall balance, as when <hi>Paul</hi> thought with himſelfe how good and glorious it would bee for him to be quit of this miſerable pilgrimage of Life, and the glory hee ſhould receiue by Death, then fell hee to his <hi>Cupio Diſſolvi,</hi> and the balance weighed on Deaths ſide; but conſidering the good that the Church was to receiue by his ſtaying, then otherwiſe. So was it with them of old to whom the joyes of Heaven were but
<pb facs="tcp:14511:43"/>
ſhadowed by MOSES and the reſt not ſo openly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed as to us.</p>
                  <p>But divers expound this place myſtically, for the death and hell of ſinne. For without doubt in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death wee praiſe God better than in this dying life. Yea, it is ſaid that DIVES knew ABRAHAM in Hell, and had a Charitable care of his Brethren on earth, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>CERTEINE MEDITATIONS, By <hi>ABRAHAM HOLLAND.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Commended and bequeathed to his dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Mother, Mrs. ANNE HOLLAND, his deere Siſters, <hi>A. H. M. H.</hi> and <hi>E. A.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Let the words of my mouth and the meditations of my heart bee alwayes acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord, my ſtrength and my Redeemer.</p>
                  <p>From this houre, O Lord, I haue vowed to ſerue thee, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of my life.</p>
                  <p>I beleeue, O Lord, helpe my unbeleefe.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="meditation">
                     <head>MEDITAT. 1.</head>
                     <p>LORD! let mee carefully examine my ſelfe what I was, now am, and what I may bee. I was (O Lord) before the inſpiring of thy powerfull breath into a dead piece of clay, Nothing: I am by the malice of Sinne in ready way to Perdition: I may
<pb facs="tcp:14511:44"/>
bee ſodainly through the reward of ſinne worſe than Nothing: I was (O Lord) before I was, Predeſtinate by thy depth of wiſedome, either to eternall Glory, or euerlaſting Sorrow: I am almoſt uncertaine, poore worme as I am, by the innumerable heape of mine owne ſinnes, and the infinite goodneſſe, and mercies of CHRIST, which ſhall light on mee: I may bee by a too late and falſe, or a true and contrite repentance, ſubiect to either. I was (O Lord) in my Mothers wombe conceiued in the fouleneſſe of Sinne: I am (O good Lord!) a dayly heaper of actuall Sin upon ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Corruption: What can I then expect but that I juſtly may be the ayme &amp; marke of thy impartiall ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? But (O Sweet Lord!) I was loued of thee before I was borne: am daily preſerued by thee though in the middeſt of my iniquities: and am in hope that through the all-ſufficient Merits and Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of thy bleſſed Sonne, to bee ſaued after death from the power of Sinne and Hell, and with him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified eternally: Let me then with ſhame remember what I was, and bluſh with ſorrow what I am, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent with ſorrow what I may bee, and tremble.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="meditation">
                     <head>MEDITAT. 2.</head>
                     <p>LEt mee (O Lord) judicially both contemne and feare this thing called Death: Let mee (O Lord) feare it as a man may, being the ſeparation of his beſt acquaintance the Soule and Body; let mee contemne the ouglineſſe of it as being a Miniſter to bring both ſoule and body to a more ſweet familiaritie: Let me feare it as it is the way to Hell, but contemne it being
<pb facs="tcp:14511:44"/>
the gate of Heauen; Feare it, as the wayes of Sinne; Contemne it, being the reward and pay of a long mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery: Let mee feare not the Arreſt of it, but the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: let me contemne it, knowing CHRIST is my Common-Bayle: Feare it, as a Monſter; but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it as being Naturall. Let mee not ſee the face of it without trembling, but embrace with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>A Briefe Meditation.</head>
                     <p>MY heart is broken (O Lord) and my diſtracted thoughts wander vp and downe to finde out thy Mercy, mercy I ſeeke (O Lord;) judgement ſitteth at thy feet (juſt God) and Mercy on thy right hand, mercifull Father: giue her leaue a little (O God) to ſhew her pleaſing countenance unto me the moſt vile, hainous, and preſumptuous of all ſinners.</p>
                     <p>O LORD, wee haue ſinned, and thou haſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (O Lord) wee ſtill ſinne and thou ſtill doeſt puniſh, giue us Grace (Good Lord) that wee may ſinne no more, that thou mayſt deſiſt from puniſhing. Let us die (O Lord) that wee may not die, and ſo ſtrictly by the witneſſe of our Conſciences judge and Condemne our ſelues that wee be neither ſeuerely judged nor juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned by thee: who both canſt, and deſireſt, if wee will truely repent ſhew thy Iudgement milde, and thy Mercy infinite. Lord, as of mee haue Mercy on all and ſhow the light of thy Countenance, and we ſhall (O Lord) bee whole. AMEN.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:45"/>
                     <head>A Meditation against the feare of Death.</head>
                     <p>ON the ſodaine I cannot chooſe but thinke them madmen or children, who ſtand in feare of Death, and yet me thinkes euen thus they are wrong-named, ſince neither Mad men, Fooles nor Children, feare Death; alas! ſhall ſimplicitie, and ſenceleſſe Folly doe more with them, than reaſon or Religion can doe with us? Shall the Sea-toſt Mariner be ſorrie that from ten thouſand dangers of the Sea hee is arriued at his ſafe and long-deſired Haven? Shall the ſterved Priſoner repine if after many yeares wofull Captiuitie hee be at laſt ſet at wiſhed Libertie? Shall the tormented Sick-man grudge if from a long and languiſhing Diſeaſe, a ſpeedy medicine reſtore him to his former perfect health? Is not our Life a ſea of troubles? A lothſome dungeon? A lingring ſickneſſe? Is not Death the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Pilot that guides us to Heaven? Is not hee the good Iudge that ſets us at libertie? The skilfull Phyſician that cures our Mortalitie, and reſtores us to Eternall life? What doe we elſe by deſiring long life, but like the ingratefull <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> deſire to Continue at their former Fleſh-pots, in making Brick and Clay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hard taskmaſters, in the Egipt of this ſinfull world, and ſo keepe from the Canaan of neuer-decaying hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe?</p>
                     <p>Is it not madneſſe in deſiring Long life to refuſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life? Shall wee be ſuch cowards to feare a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow?
<pb facs="tcp:14511:45"/>
the ſeperation of the Soule from God onely indeed is Death, the ſeperation of the Soule from the Body is but the ſhadow of Death. Shall we bee ſuch fooles to ſeeke to ſhun that which neuer man could ſcape? Shall we bee ſo faint-hearted to feare a thing ſo common and certaine? Was euer poore Labourer ſorie after his painefull dayes worke to repoſe himſelfe in ſleepe? Shall wee then ouerlaboured by a toileſome life grudge to goe to our ſweet, long and Care-ending ſleepe? Shall wee deſire ſtill to bee in our Nonage, and not like heires of Eternity, receiue our euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Inheritance? Our life is a Baniſhment from the heauenly Ieruſalem; ſhall wee bee grieued by Death to returne from Exile? Why feare wee Death which is but the Funerall of our Vices, the reſurrection of our Graces, and the day wherein God payes us our wages. Life is neuer ſweet to them that feare Death: neither can he feare any Enemy that feares not death? Did ſome of the Heathen, but reading an uncertaine Diſcourſe of Life hereafter, ſeeke their owne Death to come unto it; and ſhall wee, certaine that there is a Life hereafter full of unſpeakeable felicitie, bee affraid of the way which GOD hath ordained as a paſſage to it? Death is our yeare of Iubile, and ſhall wee not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in it? Let euery one then (O Lord) who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to bee free'd from ſinning and offending thee, cry out with PAVL, <hi>I deſire to bee diſſolved and to bee with</hi> CHRIST.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:46"/>
                  <head>A PRAYER Made and vſed with Companie in the aforeſaid Viſitation.</head>
                  <p>O Eternall GOD! to whom by Creation wee owe our Beeing from nothing: by Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thy holy Spirit a better beeing from worſe than nothing: by Redemption and Adoption a joynt Inheritance and Brother-hood with the King of Glory IESVS CHRIST, by whom wee are bold to call thee Father, neither art thou aſhamed to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge us Sonnes. For all thy benefits (O Lord) wee giue thee moſt humble thankes, in that it hath pleaſed thee to preſerue us to this time from the dangers of Hell and Death: but eſpecially (O good Lord) that thou haſt giuen us a ſence and feeling of our owne ſinnes and miſery, ſo that wee may call for Mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee goe into the Graue and bee ſeene no more: Wee moſt humbly and upon the Knees of our ſoules doe thanke thee (O Lord!) that in this thy great Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, this great Aſſizes of thine, this fearefull Plague wherein the Graue hath ſwallowed up ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; that it hath pleaſed thee to command thy ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Miniſter the <hi>Deſtroying Angell</hi> but gently to touch us, with an <hi>Arrow</hi> that was not pointed with Death, as if hee had ſayd to us: <hi>Goe away Sinne no more
<pb facs="tcp:14511:46"/>
leſt a worſe thing fall upon you.</hi> Wee confeſſe (O Lord) that our ſinnes deſerued equally, yea more than theirs, whom thou haſt taken away, and yet (O Lord) wee ſtill remaine to praiſe thy Name <hi>in the land of the Living.</hi> Which if thou doeſt continue (O Lord) thou haſt ingaged us to a ſodaine and ſpeedy newneſſe of life, with true Contrition for our former moſt hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſinnes, and a living <hi>in Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our life.</hi> But if ſo bee this bee but a gleame of thy mercy to trie our Faith and Conſtancy, and that thou haſt ordained at this time to make an end of our liues moſt wretched Pilgrimage, thy will bee done (O Lord.) But ô ſpeake Peace unto our Soules that they need not tremble at this great Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. O Lord, wee know Death is but a ſhadow, and the feare of it more terrible than it ſelfe. Let nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ouglineſſe of it nor of our ſinnes diſtract our mindes when they haue moſt need to bee buſie in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining thy grant of a better life. Blot out all our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences (O Lord) and the manifold ſinnes of our youths, make them (O Lord) though they bee <hi>red as Scarlet,</hi> yet, <hi>as White as the wooll of thy immaculate Lambe</hi> CHRIST IESVS. <hi>Waſh them (O Lord) in his Blood and by his wounds let us bee healed</hi> from the ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſores and ulcers of putrified and feſtred Sinne: So that (O Lord) we may ſmile at Death and embrace the very terrour of it. Repell (O Lord) the Divell and all his miniſters, who in theſe times of affliction are moſt ready to lay before our weake ſoules a large Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue and bill of our moſt haynous offences, telling us that thou art a juſt GOD, and wilt not heare the
<pb facs="tcp:14511:47"/>
prayers of ſuch great offenders: but (O Lord) <hi>there is Mercy with thee that thou mayeſt bee feared</hi>; yea, that thou mayeſt bee loued. Grant (O Lord) that though wee be euen ſwallowed vp of death and deſperation, yet wee may lay hold upon the precious Merits of thy deare Sonne and our loving Saviour, ſo that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in life or death, wee may crie with a true Faith and Comfort. <hi>Come Lord</hi> IESVS, <hi>come quickly.</hi> To whom with thee the Father and the Holy Ghoſt bee all honour and glory, now and ever. AMEN.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:47"/>
                  <head>A <hi>Vale</hi> to his best Part.</head>
                  <l>DId not Religion controll</l>
                  <l>I would ſay; Farewell my Soule,</l>
                  <l>But ſo much as may depart,</l>
                  <l>Farewell, I ſay, my ſoule and heart!</l>
                  <l>Since from thee I'me forc'd to flie</l>
                  <l>I'le enter no meane Hereſie,</l>
                  <l>But will thinke it may agree</l>
                  <l>A Body without Soule, that's thee:</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt my ſoule (and ſo behau'd)</l>
                  <l>I am in hope it may bee ſau'd:</l>
                  <l>My heart's in thee, or mee, or both,</l>
                  <l>And yet if ſeperate, I am loth</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt not all, know for thy part,</l>
                  <l>I am a niggard of my heart.</l>
                  <l>Farewell I ſay, and though 'tis paine</l>
                  <l>To ſay this word, Farewell againe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:48"/>Farewell, yea ſo that thou may'ſt liue</l>
                  <l>A thouſand <hi>Vales</hi> I will giue.</l>
                  <l>That this <hi>Vale</hi> true appeare</l>
                  <l>Take a Farewell, and a Teare,</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>From thy</hi> A. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:48"/>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:49"/>
                  <head>Abraham Holland, Hauing made many EPITAPHS for others, made this <hi>Epitaph</hi> for himſelfe, and on his Death bed, dictated it to his Brother, <hi>H. H.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>PAſſenger that wilt beſtow</l>
                  <l>So much time to read this, know,</l>
                  <l>Here's one a laſting ſleepe doth take</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Chriſts</hi> Trumpet bid him wake:</l>
                  <l>This is that Gole whereto the man</l>
                  <l>That lyeth here interred ran,</l>
                  <l>This the Race-end, to which at most,</l>
                  <l>Jt can be ſaid that hee rode Post.</l>
                  <l>Let Him ſleepe quiet, and doe Thou</l>
                  <l>Leaue Sinne, not by and by, but now,</l>
                  <l>Delay not houres which ſwiftly glide</l>
                  <l>As a full Torrent or quicke Tide.</l>
                  <l>Knowing thus much, good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, paſſe,</l>
                  <l>But with this Thought, <hi>I am, He was.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Denatus</hi> 
                        <date>18. Februarij, 1625.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto theſe Post-humes is added:</p>
                  <p>NA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MACHJA.</p>
                  <p>OR, A POETICALL DESCRIPTION OF the cruell and bloudie Sea-fight or Battaile of LEPANTO: (Most memorable.)</p>
                  <p>BY ABRAHAM HOLLAND.</p>
                  <p>Reviſed by the Author, and now againe Publiſhed.</p>
                  <p>Printed for HEN: HOLLAND. M.DC.XXVI.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:50"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:50"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER, that asketh, what, when, and where, was this Battaile of LEPANTO?</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare of CHRIST IESVS, 1571. His o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Arch-Enemie the Great <hi>Turke,</hi> having had many Victories by Land in ſundry Nations, as well in ſubduing whole Countries as in taking ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrong Cities and Caſtles from the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> which confined neere his Territories, enforcing the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> either to renounce their holy Faith, or to endure unſpeakeable Slavery themſelues, their Wiues and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, beeing daily bought and ſolde in open Markets, like Horſes, Oxen, and Aſſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:51"/>The <hi>Turke</hi> by this time had Conquered many Ilands and Cities bordering upon the Sea: by meanes whereof hee was greatly enriched and ſtrengthened with Gallies and other maine Forces. And in this yeare, 1571. knowing a Diviſion amongſt divers <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes, as well for matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as for affaires of State: Vpon hope of which advantage, hee aſſembled and furniſhed a mightie Armie of Gallies, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thereby to become Soveraigne of the Sea, and Lord of the Land, at one inſtant.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch was the great Mercy of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie GOD that he ſtirred up the hearts of many <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes, (the Queene of <hi>Englands</hi> ayde beeing not wanting) who conjoyned together, and furniſhed a very ſtrong defenſible Navie of Ships, Gallies, and Galliaſſes: And encountred with the <hi>Turkes</hi> at <hi>Lepanto</hi> (which lyeth in part of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania</hi> in <hi>Turkie:</hi>) And at the time of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, the Winde changed on the <hi>Turkes</hi> ſide, and came on the backe of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and carried the ſmoke of all their Shot upon the <hi>Turkes</hi> Gallies, Foiſts, and Brigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines: ſo as they could not well ſee how to
<pb facs="tcp:14511:51"/>
defend themſelues or offend their Enemies: which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> well obſerving, with all religious Reſolution, right brauely gaue Charge and chaſe upon the Miſcreants; and ſunke and tooke of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Gallies full Two hundred and thirtie, and at that Fight ſlew aboue Thirtie thouſand <hi>Mahometiſts,</hi> beſides a great number of Priſoners taken by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi>: and aboue Twelue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand redeemed by force from <hi>Turkiſh</hi>-ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In this bleſſed Victorie, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> loſt not aboue ſeven or eight Gallies, nor of them aboue Eight thouſand perſons ſlaine.</p>
                  <p>This Overthrow to CHRISTS Enemies was done, the Sixt day of October, 1571.</p>
                  <p>And the Ninth of November following, amongſt other <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes the Newes being brought over land to Queene ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH (of ever bleſſed and immortall memory.) Shee commanded the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> to giue Almightie GOD hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heartie thankes, <hi>Her Sacred ſelfe</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the ſame: The <hi>Londoners</hi> alſo made Bonfires, and ſhowed other pleaſant ſignes of rejoycing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:52"/>
Now followeth the Patheticall-poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Deſcription of the ſame:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Vale.</hi> H. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:52"/>
                  <head>NAVMACHIA, Or the Poeticall Deſcription of a <hi>Bloody</hi> Sea-fight.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Sun once lift vp his burning Lampe</l>
                     <l>On top of hils, and fiery ſteeds gan ſtampe</l>
                     <l>Along the blew-floor'd skie, the Charriotier</l>
                     <l>Made his firce horſes run a full Carreir:</l>
                     <l>He whipt 'em on, ſo that their blood there ſhed,</l>
                     <l>Made the cleare Balcon of the Eaſt looke red.</l>
                     <l>He poſted on as if he meant not ſtay</l>
                     <l>To make a Summer, but a winters day:</l>
                     <l>Or as if he had wager'd that his teame,</l>
                     <l>Sooner than wont ſhould ſouze in weſtern ſtreame:</l>
                     <l>The ſteeds themſelues with ſpeed vnvſuall flie,</l>
                     <l>As frighted at this ſea-bred Prodigie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There came along cutting deepe <hi>Neptunes</hi> brow,</l>
                     <l>A miſty maſſe, to call't I know nor how:</l>
                     <l>Whether a running Towne, or wauing Wood,</l>
                     <l>Or moouing Delos tumbling on the Flood.</l>
                     <l>Which ſeene a farre ſcud on the watry way,</l>
                     <l>Prodigious <hi>Affrick</hi> ſeemd, or <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who getting <hi>Neptunes</hi> Paſ-port, came to ſee</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:53"/>Their Siſter <hi>Europe</hi> in her brauery.</l>
                     <l>At whoſe approch the curled billowes rore,</l>
                     <l>And as it comes fearefully roll before.</l>
                     <l>Th' oppreſſed tower-like Whales lie bellowing vnder,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Neptune</hi> ſeemes t' vſurpe his brothers thunder.</l>
                     <l>The ſilent Fiſh preſaging future bloud,</l>
                     <l>Againſt their kind run frighted into th' mud:</l>
                     <l>And had they wings, would from the Sea haue broken,</l>
                     <l>And but for churliſh nature would haue ſpoken</l>
                     <l>To manifeſt their feare, yet what they might,</l>
                     <l>They fled apace to ſhun the dreadfull ſight.</l>
                     <l>And flying from the Sea in trembling ſhiuers,</l>
                     <l>With their thicke ſholes peſter'd the leſſer riuers.</l>
                     <l>The Oceans King feeling ſuch weight on's backe,</l>
                     <l>With leaning on his Trident made it cracke.</l>
                     <l>Had it not been immooveable, they ſay,</l>
                     <l>The earth this time would faine haue fled away.</l>
                     <l>Th'amazed ſhore as the fleet neere ſounds,</l>
                     <l>Almoſt forgot to keep's ordained bounds.</l>
                     <l>The earth and ſhore ſo trembling, you'd ha ſayd,</l>
                     <l>Feare, not incloſed winds, this Earth-quake made.</l>
                     <l>Fame with her feet on earth, and head i'th' ſpheares,</l>
                     <l>With wings plum'd full of wonderment and feares,</l>
                     <l>Flies ore the land, and forth her rumours blazes,</l>
                     <l>And with increaſing dire reports amazes.</l>
                     <l>The ſtouteſt courages ſtill as ſhe goes,</l>
                     <l>Sh'augments the power and valour of the foes.</l>
                     <l>Tel's of ſtrange engines, inſtruments, and whips,</l>
                     <l>Framed to act their cruelty, and ſhips</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:53"/>Prodigious bigge, vizards, and murthering Kniues,</l>
                     <l>Butcherly malls for ſlaughter, Halters, Giues,</l>
                     <l>And all the men like Giants: Thus ſhe flies</l>
                     <l>Increaſing ſtill the Terrour, and with lies</l>
                     <l>Makes a true feare: and ere it was well ſpide,</l>
                     <l>She ſweares the fleet in ſuch a place did ride.</l>
                     <l>And all the men were landed: ſuch a towne,</l>
                     <l>Was battered, and ſuch a caſtle downe.</l>
                     <l>Another Citty without doubt was ta'ne,</l>
                     <l>And at the winning of it, more men ſlaine</l>
                     <l>Then it contain'd: Thus monſtrous Fame doth range her,</l>
                     <l>And maketh feare more fearefull then the danger.</l>
                     <l>And thus as Fame her flying terrour doubles,</l>
                     <l>Each diuers ſtate is wract with diuers troubles.</l>
                     <l>Great men doe feare that they here-by ſhall fall,</l>
                     <l>Which the poore man doth hope to riſe withall.</l>
                     <l>The peaceable do hereby feare annoyment,</l>
                     <l>The needy Ding-thrift hereby hopes imployment.</l>
                     <l>The Coward this way feareth he ſhall die:</l>
                     <l>The valiant looke for immortality.</l>
                     <l>The louing Wife doth feare her Husbands life,</l>
                     <l>And he as much is troubled for his Wife.</l>
                     <l>Stout old men wiſh that they were young againe,</l>
                     <l>Baſe young men wiſh that they in age were ta'ne:</l>
                     <l>Women for feare weepe out their tender eyes,</l>
                     <l>Dumbe Infants almoſt anſwer to their cryes.</l>
                     <l>In all the diſagreement, which is here,</l>
                     <l>They all agree in this, that all doe feare.</l>
                     <l>The Beacons now were fir'd: as if the flame</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:54"/>Euen here a contrarity did claime</l>
                     <l>Againſt the water, whoſe prodigious light,</l>
                     <l>Men feard on land, as in a ſtormy night</l>
                     <l>The Sailers feare <hi>Orion,</hi> which but ſeene,</l>
                     <l>Pronounces vnto Mariners, the teene</l>
                     <l>Of angry clouds. And now thoſe noble Spirits,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe onely ayme is by their haughty merits</l>
                     <l>To out-liue fate, and for their Countries good</l>
                     <l>Thinke it a glory to powre forth their blood,</l>
                     <l>Meete all together, as deuote to giue</l>
                     <l>Their owne liues that their Countrymen may liue,</l>
                     <l>Thus in all ages, and we ſtill may trie</l>
                     <l>Of life the worthi'ſt, readieſt are to die.</l>
                     <l>Who haſting to their ſhips in ſpeed, begin</l>
                     <l>To ſhew the aduerſe party ſhould not win</l>
                     <l>Without reſiſtance, ſhewing there were made</l>
                     <l>Men as well to defend as to invade.</l>
                     <l>Our Admirall breath's forth a ſtout All-arme,</l>
                     <l>The aduerſe fleet Ecchoed rebounding, Arme.</l>
                     <l>As when by ſound of hollow braſſe, or tin</l>
                     <l>The ſcatterd bees, buzzing with murmurous din,</l>
                     <l>Throng in one heape, to ſome well-branched tree,</l>
                     <l>Leauing their ſweet, and harmeleſſe the every;</l>
                     <l>And ſo by craft betray'd, are in a trice</l>
                     <l>Captiu'd all in their narrow Edifice.</l>
                     <l>Thus at their Captaines voice, the vulgar ſort</l>
                     <l>To their aſſigned ſtations reſort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>With quicke confuſed haſt the tumult's led,</l>
                     <l>And ſpeed, by too much ſpeed, is hindered,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:54"/>All to their charge with trembling boldnes run,</l>
                     <l>With quaking hand one charges firſt his Gun,</l>
                     <l>Another girds his threatning ſword on's ſide;</l>
                     <l>Some claſps their ſteelie Helmets; ſheilds are tied</l>
                     <l>On trembling armes apace, that one might then</l>
                     <l>Haue thought th' had been all mouing Iron men.</l>
                     <l>And now the Martiall ſteely-pointed ſtaues</l>
                     <l>Were ſnatch't in haſt: the heauy murdring Glaues:</l>
                     <l>Bowes bent to ſlaughter: weighty Courtelaxe:</l>
                     <l>And Darts Death's Harbingers; the black bill, axe.</l>
                     <l>And other armes which before ruſting ſtood,</l>
                     <l>But now are brought forth to be skour'd with blood.</l>
                     <l>Our ſaile-wing'd fleet launcheth fro'th'shore now eaſed</l>
                     <l>Of it's dread burden, nor was th'earth more pleaſed</l>
                     <l>To ſee from her one hideous terrour paſt,</l>
                     <l>That grieu'd to ſee another come as faſt.</l>
                     <l>One might haue thought the battell was begun</l>
                     <l>To ſee how <hi>Neptune</hi> firſt was thorough run,</l>
                     <l>How the ſterne braſſe his curled forehead tore,</l>
                     <l>And trembling waues were ſtrucke by cruell oare.</l>
                     <l>Each Fleet the Captaines had deuided ſoone,</l>
                     <l>Into the formes of the halfe-circled Moone;</l>
                     <l>But as their furious hornes together met,</l>
                     <l>Theſe two halfe-moones a full Moone did beget;</l>
                     <l>Which like to that in Heauen, as it did goe,</l>
                     <l>Made the fleet waters ſtrangely Ebbe and Flow.</l>
                     <l>Now as with proud aduance they neerer came,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe beaſts which gaue the ſaile-rul'd veſſels name,</l>
                     <l>With an aſpect more grim than is their life,</l>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:55"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:55"/>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:56"/>As breathing nought but bate, and balefull ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>Come fiercely forward all, as if from thence</l>
                     <l>They meant to moue their painted Reſidence.</l>
                     <l>The Lyon, Elephant, and ſauage Hogge,</l>
                     <l>The Libard, Tygre, Ounce, and cruell Dogge</l>
                     <l>Sternely affront each other, one might gueſſe</l>
                     <l>In midſt of Sea a ſauage Wilderneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Wherein with admiration, one might ſee</l>
                     <l>So many a fierce wild beaſt, ſo many a Tree.</l>
                     <l>But now our valiant Generall traverſing</l>
                     <l>About the fleet encourag'd them, rehearſing</l>
                     <l>This ſpeech, wherein he brauely did exhort</l>
                     <l>To th' Fight, which ready cut th' Oration ſhort.</l>
                     <l>Courage braue friends, and that is all I pray,</l>
                     <l>Strength cannot want, where Courage leads the way,</l>
                     <l>But what need I th' vndaunted hearts excite,</l>
                     <l>Of them whoſe eies me thinks already fight;</l>
                     <l>Looke as ye doe, and ye ſhall neuer need</l>
                     <l>Weapons, or hands to make your foes to bleed.</l>
                     <l>Your look's ſhall ſtrike'em dead, and warlike ſight</l>
                     <l>Shall put your fearefull enemies to flight.</l>
                     <l>What ere ye aime at, heere before you lie,</l>
                     <l>Honour, Reuenge, Spoile, Riches, Victorie:</l>
                     <l>Which if they mooue not, ſee your Natiue Land,</l>
                     <l>Your Nurſe, your Mother, ſee how ſhe doth ſtand</l>
                     <l>A farre to marke, which of you beſt ſhall render</l>
                     <l>The Meed of Nurture, who ſhall beſt defend her,</l>
                     <l>Them will ſhe honour; brauely then driue backe</l>
                     <l>This vaſt Sea-monſter, which is come to racke</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:56"/>Your Nurſſes entrailes, com't but once to Land,</l>
                     <l>The very Earth will be affraid to ſtand</l>
                     <l>It's cruell brunt, whither if reach it can,</l>
                     <l>The blood and teares will make an Ocean</l>
                     <l>Deeper than this: I ſee'em now repaire</l>
                     <l>(O let my <hi>Omen</hi> vaniſh into aire.)</l>
                     <l>Vnto our Land; ſee how like Wolues they rage</l>
                     <l>About the coaſts, ſparing nor ſex, nor age.</l>
                     <l>See how they pull ſtrong wals of Citties downe,</l>
                     <l>Leauing the men as naked as the Towne.</l>
                     <l>They raze your ſacred Temples, and not leaue</l>
                     <l>A hallowed place, where after ye may heaue</l>
                     <l>Your hands for aide to heav'n: Your Altars frames,</l>
                     <l>Theſe wicked wretches, with prophaned flames</l>
                     <l>Sacrifice to their anger; yea they dare</l>
                     <l>To open Ghoſtly Tomb's, and thence lay bare</l>
                     <l>Your Anceſtors ſad Coffins: whoſe dead aſhes</l>
                     <l>In ſtead of teares, their Childrens blood be-daſhes.</l>
                     <l>They dragge our ancient Parents vnto ſlaughter,</l>
                     <l>Anſwering their dying grones with cruell laughter.</l>
                     <l>Our younger Wiues and Siſters they deflour,</l>
                     <l>And baſel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> make our neereſt kinſmen, our</l>
                     <l>Moſt hated foes; our tender infants rawle</l>
                     <l>Scarce borne, being borne vnto their funerall.</l>
                     <l>Theſe things, which, heav'n be thank't, I but ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>Vnleſſe yee helpe will once aduance our foes.</l>
                     <l>Say that our Nauy be farre leſſe than theirs,</l>
                     <l>Haue not great ſhips, amids their ſwift carriers</l>
                     <l>Beene ſtaid by little Remoraes: Then on,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:57"/>And let not this cold Element, whereon</l>
                     <l>We are to fight, quench thoſe couragious flames</l>
                     <l>Which burne in euery manly breſt, that aimes</l>
                     <l>At immortality, but ſtrike ſo ſterne,</l>
                     <l>That the dumbe fiſhes may heereafter learne</l>
                     <l>To ſpeake your praiſes, and each waue report</l>
                     <l>Vnto it's neighbour, in how valiant ſort</l>
                     <l>Ye fought, till that the Oceans vtmoſt bound,</l>
                     <l>And fartheſt Thule with your fame ſhall ſound:</l>
                     <l>Yea that the Sun, when he at night ſhall preſſe</l>
                     <l>This way, may goe and tell th' Antipodes</l>
                     <l>What acts he ſaw; nor yet of ayd deſpaire,</l>
                     <l>The Sea it ſelfe, if need ſhall aske, will ſpare</l>
                     <l>A thouſand of his ſtreaming arm's for you,</l>
                     <l>All fiſh prooue ſword-fiſh to fight for our due.</l>
                     <l>Thinke for no refuge heere to flie, your hand</l>
                     <l>Not feet muſt bring you backe againe to land:</l>
                     <l>No longer will the time with vs diſpence,</l>
                     <l>What my ſpeech wants, my ſword ſhall recompence.</l>
                     <l>Now 'twixt a thouſand liues, a thouſand death's</l>
                     <l>Of time one little winged minute breath's</l>
                     <l>The loud-mouth'd Gun, onely expects the fire,</l>
                     <l>At touch of which, as burnt, it ſhould expire</l>
                     <l>It's skrieking voice, groning that ſo much death</l>
                     <l>Should be accompliſh't by th'infectious breath</l>
                     <l>Of it's dire mouth; Darts ready are to part</l>
                     <l>To hide their heads in ſome ill fortun'd hart.</l>
                     <l>Arrowes, and Muskets leuel'd, ſeeme to kill,</l>
                     <l>Before they can in act, in fierie will.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:57"/>One might haue thought viewing this fearefull ſight,</l>
                     <l>'Thad bin the picture of a Navall Fight.</l>
                     <l>But harke th' amazing ſignes of battell ſound,</l>
                     <l>Making the lands remote, and rockes rebound:</l>
                     <l>The ſhrill voic't Trumpet and couragious drum,</l>
                     <l>In barbarous language bid the foes to come.</l>
                     <l>Death's horrid vizar now begins t' appeare,</l>
                     <l>In their pale faces; terrour, and gaſtly feare</l>
                     <l>In their amazed hearts doth panting riſe,</l>
                     <l>And future blood bath's in their fiery eyes.</l>
                     <l>Sterne Cruelty aduanceth in their lids,</l>
                     <l>With headlong fury ſtalking in the mids:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Apelles</hi> preſent here or one ſo skil'd,</l>
                     <l>Might haue made pictures hence that would haue kil'd.</l>
                     <l>The thundring Ord'nance now began to rent</l>
                     <l>Th' amazed aire, the flames before it ſent,</l>
                     <l>Seeme lightning, and as deadly bullets flie:</l>
                     <l>Prodigious haile ſeem'd to powre downe the skie,</l>
                     <l>Smoake made a clowdy miſt, and all together</l>
                     <l>Seeme on the ſea to make tempeſtuous weather.</l>
                     <l>To call for ayd here, ſtands as much in ſtead,</l>
                     <l>As in that place, when from a doubtfull head.</l>
                     <l>The ſeauen-mouth'd <hi>Nilus,</hi> with a deſperate ſhocke,</l>
                     <l>Headlong doth tumble from th' amazed rock;</l>
                     <l>Making the people on the neighbouring ſhelues,</l>
                     <l>That hearing him, they cannot heare themſelues;</l>
                     <l>Thus the fights noyſe made many a man to fall</l>
                     <l>In troublous death, a ſilent Funerall.</l>
                     <l>Alas thoſe Elements which vſe t' vp hold</l>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:58"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:58"/>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:59"/>Our crazy liues, with their iuſt heate, and cold,</l>
                     <l>Making compact our bodies conſtitution,</l>
                     <l>Striue now to cauſe it's vtter diſſolution</l>
                     <l>The quicke and piercing fire, as it doth burne</l>
                     <l>Their wofull carkaſſes, doth freezing turne</l>
                     <l>Their minds to quaking feare, and chill deſpaire,</l>
                     <l>The liquid, flitting, and all-ſearching aire</l>
                     <l>Admitts remorſles ſhot, and murdring darts</l>
                     <l>Denying breath at laſt to coole their harts.</l>
                     <l>The theeviſh water though it ran away</l>
                     <l>With ſuttle ſhifts, did notwithſtanding ſlay</l>
                     <l>And ſwallow moſt, with a deuouring flood,</l>
                     <l>Onely poore earth, ſtarke, ſtill, aſtoniſhed ſtood.</l>
                     <l>Who viewing this would not haue thought a wonder</l>
                     <l>That without raine, wind, lightning, haile, or thunder</l>
                     <l>Or hidden ſhelues, or rocks ſea-ambuſht back</l>
                     <l>Or any temreſt, ſhips ſhould ſuffer wrack?</l>
                     <l>That one might heere haue term'd it, chooſe you whether</l>
                     <l>A ſtrong Calme, or calme tempeſtuous wether.</l>
                     <l>See winged arrowes poſting through the skie</l>
                     <l>How quicke they haſt froth' battells rage to flie</l>
                     <l>The trembling ſpeares, as ſouldiers doe them ſhake,</l>
                     <l>Seeme at their Maiſters dangrs that they quake:</l>
                     <l>The flaſhing ſwords, which ſheathed once they ware,</l>
                     <l>Seeme now to feare, being vnarm'd and bare.</l>
                     <l>But now each fleet, each ſhip with hope-full pride</l>
                     <l>Claſh altogether, furious, ſide to ſide.</l>
                     <l>As when two winds in blacke tempeſtuous wether,</l>
                     <l>With boiſtrous wings impetuous meete together</l>
                     <l>With their vntamed and reſiſtles iuſtle,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:59"/>Making high turrets ſhake, and cedars ruſtle,</l>
                     <l>Where in light ſhirmiſh they remaine contending,</l>
                     <l>Till out of breath th' are faine to make an ending</l>
                     <l>Now death's at hand, and night together keepe</l>
                     <l>Cleare life, and dreadfull death's blacke iron ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>Fierce rage, ſad griefe, blind Fury now grow higher,</l>
                     <l>Good cauſe when ſence of touch and hearing nigher</l>
                     <l>Men now with men contend, and ſhips with ſhips,</l>
                     <l>One body 'gainſt another; here one skips</l>
                     <l>Into his enemies deck, but beaten back</l>
                     <l>He leaps to's owne, of which if ſo he lacke,</l>
                     <l>He fall's in ſea; much like a wave, whoſe head</l>
                     <l>By vrging winds vnto the ſhore is led,</l>
                     <l>And thence by breſt of the oft-drowned ſhore</l>
                     <l>Taking a blunt repulſe, for ſpight doth rore,</l>
                     <l>And ſtaggering runs backe; and is this all</l>
                     <l>Ambition aymes at, in the way to fall?</l>
                     <l>Their tired ſences labour'd in ſuch wiſe,</l>
                     <l>That they grew dull with too much excerciſe</l>
                     <l>Their troubled eyes, viewing ſuch gaſtly ſights,</l>
                     <l>Wiſht that ſad darkeneſſe cancell'd all their hights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>That horrid noiſe the battell made, was ſuch,</l>
                     <l>Hearing heard nothing, 'cavſe it heard ſo much</l>
                     <l>Taſt is of death, ranke blod pollutes the ſmell,</l>
                     <l>What feeling felt they all did feele too well.</l>
                     <l>Such a confuſion racks their ſenſes here</l>
                     <l>Th' had Reaſon now to wiſh they ſenceleſſe were.</l>
                     <l>Grim death in purple, ſtalkes vpon the hatches,</l>
                     <l>With pale and grieſly lookes ſee how he ſnatches</l>
                     <l>Hundreds a once vnto him, till the dreary</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:60"/>Lean-face't ill-favord Death of death grew weary.</l>
                     <l>See on the ſea how thouſand Bodies float</l>
                     <l>From their great ſhips haſting to <hi>Charons</hi> Boat,</l>
                     <l>Which crabbed Skuller now might thinke it meet</l>
                     <l>His old-torne Boate ſhould be new-chang'd a Fleet.</l>
                     <l>The tumults noiſe pierc't the blew-arched skie</l>
                     <l>The chryſtall Aire fill'd with a deadly crie,</l>
                     <l>Onely in this was bleſt, as blowes abounded,</l>
                     <l>It could be euer cut, yet neuer wounded.</l>
                     <l>The ſilent Earth glad that ſhee was debarr'd</l>
                     <l>From this ſad Fight, yet inwardly was heard</l>
                     <l>The dreadfull ſtrokes rebounding loud, to mone</l>
                     <l>And Eccho made her yeeld a hollow grone,</l>
                     <l>But this cauſe chiefly made her moſt to raue,</l>
                     <l>That to her due the ſea ſhould prooue a graue.</l>
                     <l>Neuer did ſtrong-breath't <hi>Aeolus</hi> diſturbe</l>
                     <l>The ſea ſo much, When he can hardly curbe</l>
                     <l>His madding pages, when they raging muſter</l>
                     <l>To quarrell with the waues, or whiſtling bluſter</l>
                     <l>Among the well-ſet trees, and branched bowgh's</l>
                     <l>Singing through chinks of ſome decayd houſe:</l>
                     <l>Nor ſterne <hi>Orion</hi> with his ſtormy light</l>
                     <l>Appalling ſhipmen, doth ſo much affright</l>
                     <l>The ſoone moov'd ſea, as did this battels noiſe,</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Neptune</hi> anſwer'd with his bellowing voice,</l>
                     <l>Who as the Fleet's vrg'd neerer to the ſtrand</l>
                     <l>Which tumbling pace, ran frighted vp the ſand,</l>
                     <l>That had not bounds reſtrain'd his element,</l>
                     <l>His watery vaile had cloth'd the Continent.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:60"/>The fearefull winds on th' Ocean durſt not rome,</l>
                     <l>But leaſt they ſhould be ſmother'd kert at home.</l>
                     <l>And there ſat ſighing: Clouds their rane doe keepe,</l>
                     <l>Though ready at the battells ſight to weepe,</l>
                     <l>Leaſt their pure drops with gore-blood ſhould be ſtaind</l>
                     <l>So that no winds blew, nor from heauen it rain'd;</l>
                     <l>Maruaile not yet at tempeſts on the flood</l>
                     <l>So many teares ſtream'd, and ſuch ſtreames of blood,</l>
                     <l>Nor without winds are waues to be admir'd,</l>
                     <l>So many grones and dyings brea'ths expir'd.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Oceans</hi> skaly, ſilent wandring nation</l>
                     <l>Seeing pale armed troups inuade the ſtation</l>
                     <l>Of their vaſt kingdome, downe the ſanguine flood</l>
                     <l>Fearefully glide, fearing their future food.</l>
                     <l>The tender Nymph's who with their ſiluer feete</l>
                     <l>Vſe on the plaines of criſped Thetys meete,</l>
                     <l>Where tripping prettely th' are wont to dance</l>
                     <l>Themſelues, into a heauenly ſlwmbring trance</l>
                     <l>Of ſweet repoſe, at theſe inhumane ſhocks</l>
                     <l>With haire all torne creepe into th' hollow rockes</l>
                     <l>Wher ſhrouded they to meditate began,</l>
                     <l>No rocke ſo flinty as the heart of man,</l>
                     <l>The rocks though alwaies ſtruck by waters fury,</l>
                     <l>The rockes yet patient beare this iniury;</l>
                     <l>Yea <hi>Thetis</hi> ſelfe whoſe woombe enriched bare</l>
                     <l>That fearefull Thunder of the Troian war</l>
                     <l>Stubborne Achilles, who in fight did win</l>
                     <l>Such glory, wiſht that warr's had neuer bin.</l>
                     <l>So ſhe, with all her trembling watery peers</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:61"/>Augment the briniſh ſea, with briniſh teares.</l>
                     <l>Ships now begin to burne, that one might ſee</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Neptunes</hi> and <hi>Vulcans</hi> conſangunity</l>
                     <l>Yea now theſe ſhips, which free from water ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Strangly begin to ſinke with humane blood,</l>
                     <l>Which as from thence with fearefull guſh it ran,</l>
                     <l>Fill'd vp the wrinkles of the Ocean,</l>
                     <l>Making with purpoſe gaſtly gored hue,</l>
                     <l>Of one Red ſea which was before, now two:</l>
                     <l>Which ſea ſo full of Dead, it hence might come</l>
                     <l>Well to be called, <hi>Mare Mortuum.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The quaking ſhips with murmuring guns are rent,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe wounded ſides the gored ſtreames doe vent</l>
                     <l>Of dead and wounded men, who lay therein,</l>
                     <l>As if they had their Beeres or coffin's bin:</l>
                     <l>They lay therein and as the ſhips did goe</l>
                     <l>Seem'd bloody, bloodles, dead, and mooving too.</l>
                     <l>The furious fire with flames doth vndermine</l>
                     <l>The towring Maſt, made of the lofty Pine,</l>
                     <l>So that ſame tree which oft hight's Nuptiall's,</l>
                     <l>Now Cypreſſe-like doth burne at Funerall's.</l>
                     <l>And eaten by the galling flames, at laſt</l>
                     <l>Fall's downe the huge, high, heauy weighted Maſt,</l>
                     <l>And as great things are wont, fell not alone</l>
                     <l>Killing a troupe nor of it's foes, but owne.</l>
                     <l>The tacklings, ſail's, and cables now doe burne,</l>
                     <l>And fire caſts Anchors, neuer to returne.</l>
                     <l>About their eares the whiſtling bullets ſung,</l>
                     <l>And wandring wild-fire made th' affrighted throng</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:61"/>Croud into corners ſpeedily, and they</l>
                     <l>That durſt ſtand men, to ſenſles fire giue way.</l>
                     <l>As when with in the fat Trinacrian ſoile,</l>
                     <l>Inflamed <hi>Aetna</hi> doth begin to boile,</l>
                     <l>When nak't <hi>Pyracmon,</hi> with his round-ey'd fellowes,</l>
                     <l>Sweatinh heaue vp their huge ſtrong-breathed bellowes,</l>
                     <l>Thundring vpon their ſteeled Anviles top</l>
                     <l>To furniſh armour for their ſmoaky ſhop;</l>
                     <l>Their pondrous hammers, and redoubling, makes</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Enceladus</hi> belch out his ſulph'ry flakes</l>
                     <l>Of veng-full wrath, then may you ſee blacke ſmoke</l>
                     <l>Vomiring out, wrapt, in a pitchy cloke,</l>
                     <l>And the hard bowels of the mountaine, torne</l>
                     <l>By ſetter'd fire, with a ſtrange bounding borne</l>
                     <l>Vp to the cloulds, whoſe fearefull fall to ſhun,</l>
                     <l>The neighbouring people with a maz'ment, run</l>
                     <l>To ſhroudin'g Dens, hiding them cloſely vnder,</l>
                     <l>Fearing from high, and from below a thunder.</l>
                     <l>Then did th' inhumane battels fury rage,</l>
                     <l>Nor could the ſea th' increaſing flames aſſwage.</l>
                     <l>And Mars himſelfe, in Adamantine armes,</l>
                     <l>With a hoarſe voice rores out againſt all-armes.</l>
                     <l>He that would now haue travailed to hell,</l>
                     <l>Might haue ſeene weary ſweating <hi>Charon</hi> well</l>
                     <l>In feruent labour, with his moſſy oares</l>
                     <l>Tugging pale ſhaddowes to th' ore-ſwarmed ſhores;</l>
                     <l>Which on the bancks as they lamenting crept,</l>
                     <l>Wailing <hi>Cocytus</hi> in compaſſion wept.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Acheron</hi> flow'd with griefe, and as they ſay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:62"/>
                        <hi>Lethe</hi> it ſelfe could neuer forget this day,</l>
                     <l>The Furies whin'd, by <hi>Plutoes</hi> Iudgement caſt,</l>
                     <l>Who ſware their rage was farre by men ſurpaſt,</l>
                     <l>One coming heere might tired <hi>Clotho</hi> ſpie,</l>
                     <l>How ſhe could ſearſe her weary arm's apply</l>
                     <l>To turne the wheele; and <hi>Lacheſis</hi> repine</l>
                     <l>Who ſware ſhe could not threds of mortalls twine</l>
                     <l>So faſt as they were cut; you might haue ſeene</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Atropos</hi> raging with remorſles teene</l>
                     <l>And ſeeking each where for ſome greetty ſtone</l>
                     <l>To whet her ſheeres, whoſe edge was dulled growne</l>
                     <l>With too much cutting of their fatall thread,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe haples liues this gaſtfull battell ſhed.</l>
                     <l>Fire now and water did not each contend,</l>
                     <l>But ſeeme their power ſo mutually to lend,</l>
                     <l>That at this time there many a one became</l>
                     <l>Burn't in the ſea and drowned in the flame.</l>
                     <l>This one good hap to carkaſſes did fall,</l>
                     <l>Th' had fire to burn'em at their funerall.</l>
                     <l>The mangled ſhips not fearing to be drencht,</l>
                     <l>Gladly take breaches, thereby to be quencht.</l>
                     <l>But now thou <hi>Tiſiphonc,</hi> infernall Muſe</l>
                     <l>Rouzing thy ſelfe from Stygian ſleepe, peruſe</l>
                     <l>The various Images of dreary Fate</l>
                     <l>Hapning in this ſad Fight, and Intimate</l>
                     <l>Them to my mind, which well, I thinke, agree,</l>
                     <l>Not with a ſweete, and heauenly Muſe, but thee.</l>
                     <l>Th' Induſtrious Pilot ſitting at the ſterne,</l>
                     <l>VVhere in a little card, he can diſcerne</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:62"/>The vaſt vncertainetie of <hi>Neptunes</hi> haunt</l>
                     <l>Ruling ſwift ſhips by powerfull Adamant,</l>
                     <l>Here as he ſits retir'd, and watchfull minds</l>
                     <l>The frequent change of two and thirty winds</l>
                     <l>Comes an vnruly ſhot, and him doth force</l>
                     <l>To certaine death, change his vncertaine courſe,</l>
                     <l>So he that wont ſtern blaſts in truce to bind,</l>
                     <l>Could not foreſee when he ſhould looſe his wind,</l>
                     <l>From ſtormes, and Miſts of Death he could not free</l>
                     <l>Himſelfe, who wont the Tempeſts curbe, but he</l>
                     <l>Who bearding <hi>Neptune,</hi> vs'd on th' Ocean float,</l>
                     <l>Is now controll'd in <hi>Charons</hi> little boat.</l>
                     <l>The Maſter ranging vp and downe the Deck,</l>
                     <l>And wounded mortally, to him doth beck</l>
                     <l>His Mate, who haſting to his ayd in vaine</l>
                     <l>Is there together with the Maiſter ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>And at once ended with him his liues Date,</l>
                     <l>Proouing himſelfe truely the Maſters Mate.</l>
                     <l>The Trumpetter, with braue reuiuing ſound</l>
                     <l>Quickning their dying harts, is fell'd <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oth' ground,</l>
                     <l>And as in's mouth he ſtill the braſſe did wield,</l>
                     <l>His dying breath made it a dead march yeeld,</l>
                     <l>And hauing lent his Trumpet ſo much breath</l>
                     <l>In's life, it turn'd him ſome againe at's death.</l>
                     <l>The Drummer with his nimble hand repeating</l>
                     <l>His doubled blowes, without compaſſion beating</l>
                     <l>His harmleſſe drum, which ſeem'd with groning cry</l>
                     <l>To murmur at his Maiſters cruelty,</l>
                     <l>Sodenly two raſh bullets rudely come</l>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:63"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:63"/>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:64"/>Tearing both skin of drumer, and the Drum,</l>
                     <l>Drummer of life, of ſound the Drum's bereft:</l>
                     <l>So Drum, and Drummer both are ſpeechles left.</l>
                     <l>The Gunner as with nimble haſt he runs</l>
                     <l>To fire his ſeldome-vaine-reporting Guns,</l>
                     <l>His head a leaden-winged bullet hits</l>
                     <l>And his hard braine-pan into peeces ſplits,</l>
                     <l>He of a thouſand this alone might vaunt,</l>
                     <l>That of his death he was not ignorant,</l>
                     <l>And this true riddle might of him abide,</l>
                     <l>He liued once by's Death, by's life now dide.</l>
                     <l>Here comes a Captaine, with vndaunted face,</l>
                     <l>Encouraging his ſouldiers to the Chace,</l>
                     <l>And being about to ſay, be braue and bold,</l>
                     <l>An vntaught bullet rudely bids him hold,</l>
                     <l>And as death's miſt in his dull eyes did wander,</l>
                     <l>Beſeeching ayd he left to be commander,</l>
                     <l>And he whoſe voice from fainting thought to call them,</l>
                     <l>By's dying grone doth fearefully apall them:</l>
                     <l>This leader faithfull to his vtmoſt breath</l>
                     <l>Can onely now lead them the way to Death.</l>
                     <l>See how to ſteale the wauing flagg, one climbs</l>
                     <l>Vp by the cards, but being eſpied betimes</l>
                     <l>Tangled i'th' ropes, he is of life bereft,</l>
                     <l>And ſo is hang'd for his intended Theft.</l>
                     <l>But the cords burnt wherin his leggs were bound,</l>
                     <l>He gets a Pirats death both hang'd and drown'd.</l>
                     <l>Some vnder hatches cloſed, in deſpaire</l>
                     <l>Mount vp their foes with powder into the aire,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:64"/>Which done it ſeem'd a ſtrange prodigious ſight</l>
                     <l>A troupe of armed men to maske the light:</l>
                     <l>It ſeemeth yet that they no damage meant 'em,</l>
                     <l>Who the next way vp into heauen ſent 'em</l>
                     <l>Making them flie, beyond <hi>Dae'dalian</hi> skill,</l>
                     <l>In the vaſt aire, without a winged quill,</l>
                     <l>Giuing to them a ſtrange vnwonted death,</l>
                     <l>Who hauing aire too much yet wanted breath.</l>
                     <l>See ſee the lot of ſad Mortality,</l>
                     <l>Our chiefeſt help's, helpe oft to Miſerie,</l>
                     <l>Some men who came ſecure from future harmes</l>
                     <l>Inroll'd in well-proou'd ſteely clothed armes.</l>
                     <l>Fall by miſchance into the ſea's dire hand,</l>
                     <l>Whence being vnarm'd they might haue ſwom to land:</l>
                     <l>Their armes doe ſinke, and without mercy end 'em</l>
                     <l>So kill'd by that which chiefly ſhould defend 'em.</l>
                     <l>One with his Musket ready to giue fire</l>
                     <l>Aymes at another aduerſe Muskettier,</l>
                     <l>But his match miſſing fire, hee's forc't to die</l>
                     <l>By the others matches true fidelity,</l>
                     <l>By which he di'de, can ſcarc'ly well be knowne,</l>
                     <l>Whether by th' others Musket or his owne.</l>
                     <l>See there a Coward wanting heart t' abide</l>
                     <l>The daunting face of the fierce aduerſe ſide,</l>
                     <l>Slinketh behind the next, not caring whither,</l>
                     <l>Comes a mad ſhot, and kill's 'em both together;</l>
                     <l>Praiſe him in this, for though his life outdar'd him</l>
                     <l>To equall th' other, yet his death compar'd him.</l>
                     <l>Neuertheles if truly ye doe mind him,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:65"/>As in his life, in's death he came behind him.</l>
                     <l>One ſeeming now his ſide begin to faile</l>
                     <l>Shew's them their colours, while himſelfe lookes pale,</l>
                     <l>Sure by this man ſome Omen ill was ſhowne,</l>
                     <l>To keepe their colours, who could looſe his owne.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe men who chanced in the ſhips to fall</l>
                     <l>The cruell ſea was made their buirall.</l>
                     <l>And intoth' waues without remorſe were throwne,</l>
                     <l>Poore men, ſlaine by their foes, drownd by their owne.</l>
                     <l>A Fiſherman who nigh them cut the Maine</l>
                     <l>Sitting in's boate was with a bullet ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>And the barke fir'd wherein he dead did fall.</l>
                     <l>Which gratis, burnt, gaue him his Funerall</l>
                     <l>True to thy Maiſter, kind boat, who with him</l>
                     <l>Didſt oft in life, and now in death do'ſt ſwim</l>
                     <l>With him aliue in water that didſt tire</l>
                     <l>Thy waue-beat ſides, dy'ſt now with him in fire.</l>
                     <l>Yet me thinks thou ſhouldeſt not deſerue this turne</l>
                     <l>Who ſo oft plung'd with him which ſhouldeſt burne,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſaile with him t' <hi>Elyſium,</hi> ſaile the faſter,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Carons</hi> ſtead that thou maiſt waft thy Maiſter,</l>
                     <l>Strang Boat which thus we not amiſſe may call.</l>
                     <l>His Life, Death, <hi>Charon</hi> and his Funerall.</l>
                     <l>A Noble man that was a Renegate,</l>
                     <l>While he againſt his King doth boldly prate,</l>
                     <l>A ſhot takes off his head, as if twere reaſon</l>
                     <l>That he ſhould be beheaded for his Treaſon.</l>
                     <l>A baſer fellow while he dares complaine</l>
                     <l>And raile againſt his once owne Soveraigne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:65"/>A true Liege-man, as he thus boldly brags,</l>
                     <l>Striketh him vp, and his vile body drags</l>
                     <l>About the ſhip, and while he vainely begs,</l>
                     <l>Remoſles cutteth off his armes and legs,</l>
                     <l>And thinking then to throw him in the tide</l>
                     <l>Hee's caught vpon an Anchor on the ſide,</l>
                     <l>That one beholding rightly might haue ſed,</l>
                     <l>He iuſtly was hang'd, drawne, and quartered.</l>
                     <l>Some fearing ſwords, into the ſea doe flie,</l>
                     <l>And ſo for feare of death, feare not to die.</l>
                     <l>Some fall into the Ocean ſtain'd with gore,</l>
                     <l>Which from their former wounds had guſht before,</l>
                     <l>Which kill'd not them, as it from them was ſpil'd,</l>
                     <l>But entring into them againe, th'are kil'd.</l>
                     <l>Heeres one about to ſtrike, his foe doth fall</l>
                     <l>Into the ſea, before he can recall</l>
                     <l>His erring ſtroke, ſtriking the ſea to ſtay him,</l>
                     <l>The Ocean in revenge o'th blow doth ſlay him.</l>
                     <l>One fearing death doth faine to die and bleed,</l>
                     <l>And while he is in faining, dies indeed.</l>
                     <l>Another being about to ſtrike his foe</l>
                     <l>Looſeth at once his arme and threatning blow:</l>
                     <l>His left arme ſhiuering, reaches at the other,</l>
                     <l>But cut atwaine, lies with it's equall Brother,</l>
                     <l>Both ioyn'd, though both devided, as in ſpight</l>
                     <l>Of Death, they meant to part their laſt good-night,</l>
                     <l>By ſhaking hands: the miſerable truncke</l>
                     <l>As loth to part, fainting vpon them ſunke.</l>
                     <l>One ſeeing them together thus, might ſay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:66"/>There a whole bodie, all in peeces lay.</l>
                     <l>See two with ſturdy grapple, ſtriuing whether</l>
                     <l>Should overcome, both fall in ſea together;</l>
                     <l>Embracing both till they haue loſt their breath,</l>
                     <l>And ſeeme though foes in life, yet friends in death.</l>
                     <l>Two brothers ſlaine, as they together ſtood,</l>
                     <l>One then might ſweare, they were allied in blood.</l>
                     <l>Other two, who ſo nigh reſembling, were</l>
                     <l>A lov'd miſtake vnto the parents deare,</l>
                     <l>(Cruell death ſever'd them) and that one left</l>
                     <l>Poore parents knew, of errour now bereft:</l>
                     <l>He left eternall cauſe of griefe renowes,</l>
                     <l>Who ſtill aliue, ſtill his dead brother ſhew's:</l>
                     <l>And yet to them this comfort ſtill he giues,</l>
                     <l>Th'one cannot die, ſo long as th'other liues.</l>
                     <l>The wounded ſouldiers, now that all elſe failes,</l>
                     <l>To ſtop their wounds, doe teare their woful ſailes:</l>
                     <l>Poore men who after they were overthrowne</l>
                     <l>Had torne thoſe wings, wherby they might haue flown.</l>
                     <l>One with his bleeding ready to expire,</l>
                     <l>Thinks with his blood, to quench the ſhip on fire:</l>
                     <l>And ſo in mids of flames he bleeding ſtands,</l>
                     <l>Tearing new wounds with his kind cruell hands.</l>
                     <l>And grieu'd to ſee his blood ſo little profit,</l>
                     <l>He oft adds teares to helpe the quenching of it,</l>
                     <l>Till at laſt fainting he is faine to fall,</l>
                     <l>Into the ſea, which made his Funerall:</l>
                     <l>And bleeding in it from each mangled lim,</l>
                     <l>He quenched it, and it extinguiſh't him.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:66"/>See a poore wretch with both armes cut aſunder,</l>
                     <l>Diſtracted leapt into the water vnder</l>
                     <l>Meaning to ſwim, but ſee the wofull wretch</l>
                     <l>With how much toile he laboureth to ſtretch</l>
                     <l>His raw-veind ſtumps, which for his armes before</l>
                     <l>Guſh nothing now, but ſtreames of deadly gore:</l>
                     <l>Faine would he catch t'vphold his wavering life</l>
                     <l>Some kind remaine o'th ſhip, but all his ſtrife</l>
                     <l>Doth make him ſooner to be out of breath,</l>
                     <l>And wanting armes he yet embraces death.</l>
                     <l>One getteth this, by hauing loſt his eies,</l>
                     <l>In that he cannot ſee his miſeries,</l>
                     <l>Anothers legges are gone, that who him ſees</l>
                     <l>Might thinke he did begge pardon on his knees.</l>
                     <l>What refuge now is left? when if they ſhun</l>
                     <l>Th'approaching ſword, into the fire they run:</l>
                     <l>Shunning the fire, they into waterfall,</l>
                     <l>So no way wants a certaine Funerall.</l>
                     <l>Thus after ſtrange vnheard of ſort they lie,</l>
                     <l>And death, by many deaths, makes one man die.</l>
                     <l>The mangled ſhips no longer can with ſtand</l>
                     <l>Th'intruding ſea, and <hi>Mars</hi> his fiery brand;</l>
                     <l>But ſinking downward one might then haue thought</l>
                     <l>Them gone t' helpe <hi>Charon</hi> to waft ore his fraught.</l>
                     <l>The conquer'd fleet prickt now with deſperate ſtings</l>
                     <l>Of horror, wiſh their army did of wings</l>
                     <l>Onely conſiſt; but now as if it ſtood</l>
                     <l>Tyed with faſt anchors to the ſtubborne flood</l>
                     <l>Mooues not away, but void of all inſtruction,</l>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:67"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14511:67"/>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14511:68"/>Venter their owne, to haſten the deſtruction</l>
                     <l>Of their once Maiſters, who into corners creepe,</l>
                     <l>As among Wolues, a flocke of trembling ſheepe.</l>
                     <l>Much like a ſilly Doue, whoſe broken wing</l>
                     <l>Hath tried the Talons of the aiery King,</l>
                     <l>And lieth panting on the bloody ground</l>
                     <l>Striving to flie from's enemies rebound.</l>
                     <l>Alas poore bird, it wants that winged oare</l>
                     <l>Which ſhould it's wonted ſcape to it reſtore:</l>
                     <l>And ſo at length with ſilent patience crouching,</l>
                     <l>It's made a prey to the fierce bird encroching.</l>
                     <l>Thus fleet and bird lie i'th ſame wofull plight,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe onely wiſh is to be put to flight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Sunne no longer could endure to ſee</l>
                     <l>'Mongſt humane men ſuch inhumanity:</l>
                     <l>Therefore his Horſes, bathing in their fome,</l>
                     <l>With poſting ſpeed haſt to their watrie home.</l>
                     <l>Where yet a while they all amazed ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Finding in ſtead of Sea, a Sea of Blood.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:68"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:70"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:70"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:75"/>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:76"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:76"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>H. H.</hi> Authoris Fratis majoris (cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus cura ac impenſa haec praemiſſa Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma edita ſunt,)</head>
                  <head type="sub">CHARACTER.</head>
                  <l>SI quis praenomen cupiat cognoſcere nostrum,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HENRICI</hi> nomen Nympha Secrata dedit.</l>
                  <l>Jn<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuo <hi>MICHAEL</hi> festo, ſum natus &amp; ortus,<note place="margin">Septemb. 1583</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Chriſtiadis ſumpſi nomen in Aede tua.</l>
                  <l>Jlla luce mihi dil<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ta adjungitur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor<note place="margin">Septemb. 1615</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cognovi ſocium nocte priore thorum.</l>
                  <l>Hi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>MICHAEL</hi> Magnus Princeps peſsundabit omnes</l>
                  <l>Papicolas istis Tart<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra tetra patent.</l>
                  <l>Dei Pater Omnipotens, famulo mihi poſſe beatum</l>
                  <l>Sortiri in Coelo, cum <hi>MICHAELE</hi> Locum.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Aliud, CHARACTER ACROSTICON, vice EPITAPHIj.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>H</hi>ic, mihi ne totum delerent Funera Nomen,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi>ſtendam vitae rem, Lo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, Nomen, Avos.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L</hi>aude vigent patres, vid<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <hi>COVENTRIA</hi> natum,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L</hi>uce novâ: <hi>HENRICVM</hi> nomine ſignat aqua.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> patriae gr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mio, <hi>LONDINVM</hi> exc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pit adultum,<note place="margin">Anno, 1599.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rit idem: <hi>C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ara</hi> cum <hi>Pare</hi> Liber ago:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>D</hi>ivi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ico<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> est verbum: <hi>Mihi Roma peroſa:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>V</hi>ita quidem ten<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is, ſit mihi grata tamen</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S</hi>olaque post Mortem Coeleſtia dona ſuperſins.</l>
                  <closer>Mihi Roma peroſa.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="notes">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page 80. l. 4.</hi> (a) Plus male facta nocent quam benedicta de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: praedicat viva voce qui praedicat vita &amp; voce. <hi>Ib. p. l. 30.</hi> (b) Nemeſis pedes habet: Lipſ. de Conſtant. &amp; tarditatem judicii gravitate ſupplicii compenſet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page 81. l. 12.</hi> (a) Ecleſ. <hi>7.18.</hi> Qui dicunt ne appropinq<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es mihi quia immundus es. Eſ. <hi>65.5. Ib. p. l. 23.</hi> (b) Va vobis deriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, cum venerit dies judicii &amp; aperti fuerint libri conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum: Cum dicetur vobis, ecce hos puritatis deriſores &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pura eorum opera. Quid facietis tunc, cum Caeli re ve labunt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitates veſtras &amp; terra adverſus vos conſurget. <hi>Ib. p. l. 29.</hi> (c) Dicunt non faciunt hoc magnum Crimen habetur. In linguis, pietas pectore nulla manet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page 82. l. 9.</hi> (a) Mallet Deus multos: nocentes condonare quam unum innocentem condemnare. <hi>Ib. p. l. 19.</hi> (b) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt unguentum itſi vultures defugiant. Theod.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page 84. l. 3.</hi> (a) Quam bent te ambitio merſit vaniſſima ventus &amp; tumidos tumidae vos ſuperaſtis aquae. Quam bene toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us raptores orbis avaros. Hauſit inexhauſto juſta vorago maris. Theod. Be<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a in Pſal. <hi>27.2.124.3.6.</hi> Pſal. <hi>21.11.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page 85. l. 14.</hi> (a) Job <hi>4.8.</hi> Pſal. <hi>27.2.</hi> Non eſt la<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aequior ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, Quam necis artifices arte perire ſuâ. <hi>Ib. page 17.</hi> (b) Anno <hi>1602.</hi> in Londino de plaga. <hi>38244.</hi> Conſumptis tot peſte viris, tot peſte puellis, vix habuit nobis tum nova plaga locum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ibid. page l. 21.</hi> Antigones rex amicis ſun dentibus, ut ſi Athenas caperet, firmis eas &amp; validis muniret praeſidiis. Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum inquit ſcio praeſidium firmius aut ſtabilius, quam civium benevolentiam. Sic Periander ſummâ ope commitendum eſſe dixit iis, qui into regnare vellent ut benevolentia potius quam armis ſtiparentur. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Sola benevolentia ſubditorum firmiſiſſima eſt regis cuſtodia. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſius.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>IN the Eipiſtle to all the afflicted, page <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. line 5. for of, read and. Ib. p. l. 11. <hi>Maccheus.</hi> 2. p. Of the Subject, l. 25. leave out <hi>ſtill.</hi> p. 3. l. 29. ſteams. p. 4. l. 7. this. p. 33. l. 5. him. p. 69 l. 25. traſh. p. 79. l. 29. if.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:78"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:78"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:79"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:79"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:80"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:80"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:81"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:81"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:83"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:83"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:84"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:84"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:85"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:85"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:86"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:86"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:89"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:89"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:91"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:91"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:92"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14511:92"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
